<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The school of the Eucharist established upon the miraculous respects and acknowledgments, which beasts, birds, and insects, upon several occasions, have rendred to the Holy Sacrament of the altar : whence Catholicks may increase in devotion towards this divine mystery, and hereticks find there their confusion / by F. Toussain Bridoul ... ; printed in French at Lille, 1672, and now made English, and published ; with a preface concerning the testimony of miracles.</title>
            <title>Escole de l'Eucharistie. English</title>
            <author>Bridoul, Toussaint, 1595-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 180 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29396</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4495</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9439</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12642978</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12642978</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65044</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29396)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65044)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 345:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The school of the Eucharist established upon the miraculous respects and acknowledgments, which beasts, birds, and insects, upon several occasions, have rendred to the Holy Sacrament of the altar : whence Catholicks may increase in devotion towards this divine mystery, and hereticks find there their confusion / by F. Toussain Bridoul ... ; printed in French at Lille, 1672, and now made English, and published ; with a preface concerning the testimony of miracles.</title>
                  <title>Escole de l'Eucharistie. English</title>
                  <author>Bridoul, Toussaint, 1595-1672.</author>
                  <author>Clagett, William, 1646-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], xxiv, [2], 45, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Randall Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation by W. Clagett of: Escole de l'Eucharistie. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Catholic Church.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Miracles --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65044:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65044:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SCHOOL OF THE EUCHARIST ESTABLISHED Upon the Miraculous Reſpects and Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments, which BEASTS, BIRDS, and INSECTS, upon ſeveral Occaſions, have rendred to the HOLY SACRAMENT of the ALTAR.</p>
            <p>Whence Catholicks may increaſe in Devotion towards this Divine Myſtery, and Hereticks find there, their Confuſion.</p>
            <p>By <hi>F. Touſſain Bridoul,</hi> of the Society of <hi>Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in <hi>French</hi> at <hi>Lille,</hi> 1672. And now made <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and publiſhed, <hi>With a Preface concerning the Teſtimony of Miracles.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Let us view more particulary what <hi>Rational Grounds</hi> Catholicks exhibit of their belief of a Corporal preſence in the Euchariſt, and ſo of Adoration. <bibl>
                  <hi>Def. of Ador. of the Euch.</hi> p. 27. Printed at <hi>Oxford,</hi> 1687.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Randall Taylor,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:65044:2"/>
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:65044:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE TRANSLATION Concerning the Teſtimony of MIRACLES.</head>
            <p>IF the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> wants the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> it cannot be proved to come from <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apostles,</hi> by <hi>Tradition,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Fathers of the Primitive Church have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed it in their Writings: If it has had no ſuch Tradition, then the beſt Church-Authority it has to reſt upon, will be that of the <hi>Lateran</hi> and <hi>Tridentine</hi> Synods. And if they had no power to make new Articles of <hi>Faith,</hi> this Doctrine is in no good caſe to recommend it ſelf. There are but two ways remaining, I think, to put it off; one is to perſwade us, that our Learned Proteſtant Divines have ſeveral of them affirmed ſuch things concerning the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> as do amount to what the Papiſts mean by <hi>Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> and that they have laid down Principles which will ſave the <hi>Adoration of the Hoſt</hi> from being an Idolatrous Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: And this is lately attempted with great appearance of Gravity, by a certain <hi>Oxford</hi> Author: But if this will not
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:65044:3"/> do, there is yet another way left, and that is to prove <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> and the <hi>Adoration of the Hoſt,</hi> by <hi>Miracles;</hi> which has been undertaken, as by ſeveral others, ſo in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular by that Reverend <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> whoſe Collection is here Tranſlated.</p>
            <p>Our hands, I perceive, are now in about Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Worſhip of the Hoſt; and the Divines have gone ſo far in conſidering all that can be ſaid for theſe things, that 'tis pity the Controverſy ſhould not be ended all at once; to which I think nothing is wanting but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent our Adverſaries Appeal to <hi>Miracles;</hi> and that I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe cannot be more fairly done, than by expoſing to our Countrymen what themſelves have thought fit to publiſh in another Language concerning this Argument.</p>
            <p>That nothing elſe remains, is evident by what has been already done on<note n="†" place="margin">Diſcourſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtant. Doctrine of the Trin. and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion compared in a New Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue. <hi>2 parts.</hi> Tranſubſt. no Doctrine of the Primitive Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> our ſide, upon all the other Arguments, and that, as time will ſhew more fully, beyond all poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of Fair Reply. I had almoſt forgot the deſperate Defence of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> which our Adverſaries have lately made, by faſtning it to the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> being for their parts content that both ſhould ſink, if they could not ſwim together. They are, I hope, convinced by this time, that neither is their Point to be gained ſo; and that we are able to maintain the <hi>Catholick</hi> Doctrine of the Trinity, and at the ſame time to overthrow the <hi>Roman</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Tranſubſtantiation. That they cannot retreat for ſhelter to the Judgment of any Divines of this Church, is now ſhewn in the Anſwer to the <hi>Oxford</hi> Author. In ſhort, It has been<note n="*" place="margin">See Bellarm. de Sacr. Euch. <hi>l. 3. c. 23 and</hi> Diſcourſe of Euchariſt in Anſwer to the Book printed at <hi>Oxford.</hi> p. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> confeſſed by eminent men in the <hi>Roman</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, that the <hi>Scriptures</hi> do not oblige us to believe Tranſubſtantiation; and that the Fathers knew nothing of it, has been confeſſed too by a<note n="‡" place="margin">Hiſtorical Treatiſe of Tranſubſtant.</note> Learned Perſon of that Church now living, and which is ſomething more, proved alſo through the Firſt Ten Centuries. Now whether Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils
<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:65044:3"/> can make an Article of Faith of that Doctrine which is neither to be found in the Holy Scriptures, nor can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by Teſtimonies of the Ancient Fathers, but is in truth contrary to both; I am very willing the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> ſhould determine;<note n="*" place="margin">A Papiſt Miſrepreſ. and Repr. p. 33.</note> who tells us, That he is <hi>obliged to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve nothing beſides that which Chriſt taught, and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles; and if any thing contrary to this ſhould be defined and commanded to be believed, even by ten thouſand Councils, he believes it damnable in any one to receive it, and by ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees to make Additions to his Creed.</hi> A great deal leſs than this, if it had been ſaid with more ſincerity, would have ſerved our turn as well: If <hi>Ten thouſand Councils</hi> will not ſtir him in ſuch a caſe, methinks the Fourth <hi>Lateran,</hi> and the <hi>Trent</hi> Councils, the one a <hi>Weſtern,</hi> the other little more than an <hi>Italian</hi> Synod, ſhould not be able to do what <hi>Ten thouſand Councils</hi> cannot do; as for the <hi>Lateran,</hi> it is yet a diſputable point, as<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Peter Walſh's Letter to the Bp. of Lincoln, <hi>Sect. 22.</hi>
               </note> ſome of themſelves will have us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, whether the Council, or rather the Pope only, made the Decrees that bear its name; and for the <hi>Tridentine</hi> Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod, the World knows how it was from time to time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluenced by the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> ſo that when the matter comes to be look'd into, 'tis indeed the Papal Authority that gives to the world this pretended Point of Faith; but becauſe certain Popes have miſcarried in the Faith, to the great diſcredit of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair, it was neceſſary that the <hi>Popes</hi> pleaſure ſhould upon all occaſions of defining matters of Faith, be a little diſguiſed, by being conveyed to the Church under the venerable name and Formality of a <hi>Council.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſubſtantiation then has nothing left to ſtand upon, but <hi>Miracles,</hi> which is as much as to ſay, that it ſtands upon its laſt legs: <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> I find,<note place="margin">De Sacr. Euch. l. <hi>3</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> reſerved this Argument for the laſt, to prove the ſubſtantial Preſence of Chriſts Body in the Euchariſt; I know not whether he thought it the beſt
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:65044:4"/> or no; if he did, I dare undertake to anſwer what he thought his beſt Argument, and that by ſhewing, that 'tis none at all; for if we are to truſt the Old Miracles of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his Apoſtles, as without all queſtion we ought to do, then we are not to try Doctrines by new Miracles, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to try the Miracles by the Old Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Which one would think ſhould have been a Rule to all Chriſtians, ſince our Bleſſed Saviour has warned us not to truſt to <hi>Signs and Wonders,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> xxiv. 24, 25, 26.</note> no, tho they be <hi>Great</hi> ones. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I have told you before.</hi> Which Caution I muſt confeſs hath ſometimes ſurprized me with aſtoniſhment, when I conſider, what the Concluſion is for which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our Bleſſed Lords Prediction, Miracles ſhould be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; <hi>viz.</hi> to make us believe a man, when he ſays, <hi>Lo, here is Christ, or there is Christ;</hi> For what ſaid our Lord Chriſt himſelf? <hi>Believe it not,</hi> ſays he, <hi>if they ſhall ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, Behold he is in the Deſert, go not forth; Behold he is in the ſecret Chambers,</hi> or in<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> cloſe Receptacles, <hi>believe it not.</hi> I dare not ſay particularly what ſort of men are here pointed at excluſively to all others, for this would be to ſtrain beyond my reach: But this I dare ſay, 'tis not for any body's credit to come within the compaſs of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, ſince it ſeems 'tis a dangerous ſign for men to pretend to new Miracles, which if they who do ſo, will not ſee, yet at leaſt I hope others will take notice that 'tis a dangerous thing to hearken to ſuch pretenders. What St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays to the ſame purpoſe with our Saviour is ſo ſharply pointed,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſal.</hi> ii. 9, 10, 11.</note> that I had rather others ſhould go to the Bible for the words, and make the Application, than do it my ſelf for them.</p>
            <p>But by all means, let it be conſidered, that this was the way which God took, under both Teſtaments, to ſecure his People from Deluſions; that is, he warned them not to rely upon Miracles without further inquiry, but to prove the Divinity of Miracles by the eſtabliſhed Doctrine. For
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:65044:4"/> thus did <hi>Moſes</hi> inſtruct the <hi>Iſraelites, If thtre ariſe among you a Prophet, or a dreamer of dreams, and giveth thee a SIGN or a WONDER,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> xiii. 1, 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>And the ſign or the wonder come to paſs, whereof he ſpake unto thee ſaying, Let us go after other Gods (which thou haſt not known) and let us ſerve them; Thou ſhalt not hearken unto the words of that Prophet, or that Dreamer of Dreams. For the Lord your God proveth you, to know whether you love the Lord your God with all your heart, and with all your ſoul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Law of <hi>Chriſt</hi> being once eſtabliſhed, All new Miracles were to be tried by the Old Religion, whether they were of God or no: And warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was given not to give any heed to them if they came to eſtabliſh a new Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Nor do I in this matter ſay any thing that is New. For St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> amongſt others, has obſerved it long ſince.<note place="margin">De <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitate, Eccl <hi>c. 16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Let the</hi> Donatiſts, ſaies he, <hi>demonſtrate their Church if they can, not by the ſayings and rumours of</hi> Africans, <hi>not by the Councils of their Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>nor by DECEITF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L SIGNS and WONDERS, becauſe againſt theſe we are prepared and forewarned: But in the Preſcript of the Law, in the Predictions of the Prophets, in the Pſalms, in the Words of our great Paſtor himſelf; in the Preachings and Works of the Evangeliſts; That is, in all the Canonical Authorities of the Holy Books.</hi> And afterward; <hi>Let them not ſay this is true, becauſe</hi> Donatus, <hi>or</hi> Pontius, <hi>or any body elſe has done theſe and theſe Wonders, or becauſe ſome pray and prevail at the memories of our dead men; or becauſe this Brother, and that Siſter of ours, ſaw ſuch a Viſion waking, or dreamt ſuch a Dream ſleeping. Let theſe, either Fictions of Lying men, or Illuſions of deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Spirits, be all ſet aſide; for either theſe things are not true, as they are given out; or if any wonderful things be done by Hereticks, we ſhould be the more cautious; becauſe when our Lord ſaid that Deceivers ſhould ariſe, who by working
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:65044:5"/> ſome Signs, ſhould, if it were poſſible, deceive the very Elect, he added vehemently, Behold I have told you before.</hi> But perhaps it may be thought, that tho St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> would not allow Miracles to be a concluding Argument for the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> yet he believed they were an Invincible proof againſt them. No ſuch matter, I aſſure ye; for not long after, he proceeds in this manner, <hi>For neither do we ſay that we are to be believed to be in the Church of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>becauſe</hi> Optatus <hi>of</hi> Milevis, <hi>or</hi> Ambroſe <hi>of Milan, or other Biſhops of our Communion without number, have recommended that Church to which we hold; or becauſe it is made known by the Councils of our Collegues, or becauſe ſo many marvellous Cures have been wrought, ſo many Prayers heard all over the Earth in thoſe Holy Places which are frequented by our Communion; inſomuch, that the Bodies of Martyrs which had lain hid for ſo many years, were revealed to</hi> Ambroſe; <hi>and upon the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of them, one that had been Blind many years, and well known to the City of</hi> Milan, <hi>recovered his ſight; or becauſe this man had a dream, and the other taken up in Spirit, was bidden not to go over to the</hi> Donatiſts, <hi>or to come away from them.</hi> So that St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> rejected this way of proof, as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient on either ſide; and bids the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> prove their Church out of Scripture if they could, and that by plain Teſtimony of Scripture. For he has theſe remarkable words hereupon, amongſt others, <hi>But produce ſomething out of Scripture that does not need an Interpreter, and of which you cannot be convinced that it belongs to another mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and that you endeavour to wreſt it to your own purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if any body ſhould be ſo weak as to fancy, that St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s rejecting this Appeal to Miracles, muſt needs weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the teſtimony of thoſe Miracles which were wrought by <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and by <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> I muſt ſend him back to St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> again, who has well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough provided againſt this offence, by laying weight up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:65044:5"/> thoſe words of our Saviour, <hi>Behold, I have told you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</hi> For certainly we are not bound to reject all Miracles, even thoſe, againſt which there was no Divine warning before-hand, becauſe we regard not thoſe which God in his goodneſs hath warned us not to truſt to: Which I take to be the true Anſwer, and ſhall therefore inſiſt upon it by and by; tho two things may be ſaid not unfit to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered alſo.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the Miracles themſelves; The old ones had ſometimes the <hi>Finger of God</hi> in them, ſomething that ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied prudent and honeſt obſervers, that there could be no ſleight or juggle in the Caſe; and that what was done, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded any created power.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> viii. 19.</note> This the <hi>Magicians</hi> did at length confeſs of the Miracles of <hi>Moſes</hi> before <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> And of this kind were the Miracles of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> eſpecially thoſe of Curing Diſeaſes by a word, and Raiſing from the Dead. To which we may add alſo, that for the moſt part they were Miracles of goodneſs which they wrought, which was another Divine Character upon them. But now the later Miracles, we hear ſo much talk of, are many of them juſtly ſuſpected of ſleight of hand and combination, of which kind we have heard good ſtore, about the Images of the Bleſſed Virgin and the Saints: And moſt of them are ſo idle and ludicrous, that if there be any Truth in them, a wiſe man can reckon them to be no better than the illuſions of deceitful Spirits, as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks. And to find enough of theſe, I need not ſend the Reader any farther than to the Church Hiſtory of the R. F. Mr. <hi>Creſſy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Miracles wrought for the eſtabliſhment of the Law in the Old Teſtament, and of the Chriſtian Faith in the New, were not done in a corner, but openly and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly, and very often in the face of Enemies. Now the
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:65044:6"/> Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſtill pretends to the Power of Miracles, and indeed we hear of ſtrange things done amongſt them; but we <hi>ſee</hi> none. Sometimes indeed our Saviour wrought Miracles in a more private way, but then he<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> xvii. 9. <hi>Mark</hi> viii. 26.</note> charged thoſe that were concerned, to make no words of what had been done; and that, I think, leſt the want of publick Evidence ſhould be objected againſt the ſincerity of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. But things are very much altered ſince our Saviours time. The Miracles ſaid to be done in the <hi>Roman</hi> Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are indeed publickly talked of, but they are privately done, if they be done at all; for they are all done amongſt themſelves. Now what St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of <hi>Tongues,</hi> will hold true of other <hi>Miracles:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>xvi. 22.</hi> Greg. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vang Hom <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> That <hi>they are a ſign not to them that believe, but to them that believe not.</hi> St. <hi>Gregory</hi> (and ſo do many more before him) applies this to every out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward work as miraculous as that. And this at leaſt muſt be meant by it, That the principal uſe of Miracles is to bring over <hi>unbelievers</hi> to the true Faith: For which Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the perſon that is to be convinced this way, ſhould either ſee the Miracles wrought, or be aſſured that they were done by ſuch Teſtimonies, as there lies no reaſonable objection againſt. But for the ſtrange things that are ſaid to be done in the Communion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, we have only their own words for it, and as far as I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the reports they make of them, they ſeldom pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that any body ſees them but themſelves; upon which account, they want that evidence which the Miracles of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles had, and deſerve indeed but little credit. If they do ſo many Miracles, I cannot underſtand why they ſhould ſtill be done in <hi>Countries,</hi> or before <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> that are all of one <hi>mind,</hi> at leaſt all of one <hi>ſide;</hi> for thus they do not ſerve the main end of <hi>Divine</hi> Miracles, which is to be a Teſtimony to thoſe that want Conviction: And if this were all, I ſhould have great reaſon to queſtion
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:65044:6"/> whether they were <hi>Divine</hi> Miracles or not, tho I might be diſpoſed to believe ſome of the Reports.</p>
            <p>If they ſay, that the Reaſon why Miracles cannot be done before us, is our unbelief; in as much as St. <hi>Matthew</hi> reports of our Saviour when he was in his own Country, That <hi>he did not many mighty works there,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> iii. 58.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief.</hi> Nothing can be more frivolouſly alledged; For <hi>ſome</hi> mighty works were done there, at that time of which it is ſaid that he did not <hi>many.</hi> But they do none amongſt us, whither great or ſmall Miracles. And beſides this, our Saviour had alſo wrought <hi>ſome mighty works</hi> amongſt his own Countrymen before this time, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to any one that conſiders where the Goſpel of<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Joh.</hi> ii. 11. iv. 54. vii. 3, 4.</note> St. <hi>John</hi> is a ſupplement to the other Evangeliſts; ſo that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho our Lord did not think fit to multiply theſe means of conviction, upon a people ſo obſtinate, that St. <hi>Mark</hi> ſaies, <hi>He marvelled at their unbelief;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> vi. 6.</note> yet they had theſe means of conviction both Then and Formerly. And what is this to us, and to our Caſe, who have heard, and do hear ſtill of Miracles which they do in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but neither we nor our Fathers could ever ſee any of 'em? But as we muſt believe them becauſe they work Miracles; ſo we muſt believe they work Miracles, becauſe they ſay ſo.</p>
            <p>Now altho theſe two differences of the Caſe will go a great way to juſtify us in receiving the Miracles recorded in the Scriptures, while we reject the pretence of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to Miracles; yet I confeſs it does not give compleat ſatisfaction as to the point we are upon. For it may be ſometimes a difficult buſineſs to diſtinguiſh Divine Miracles from others, by the Nature of the work it ſelf. And it may alſo be asked what we are to do, if God ſhould permit ſome ſuch things to be done before our eyes, as they ſay are familiarly done, where they may ſay
<pb n="x" facs="tcp:65044:7"/> ſo ſafely enough for any bodies contradicting them. I add therefore,</p>
            <p n="3">3. There is a great difference to be made between Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles which we are not forewarned againſt, but rather warned beforehand to regard; and between Miracles that God hath not told us we ought to regard, but on the other hand hath forewarned us againſt giving any heed to them. That the <hi>Jews</hi> were obliged to examine all New Revelations by their correſpondence with the Old; and that they had been warned not to truſt to Miracles at all adventures, we have already obſerved. But becauſe it was foretold that the <hi>Meſſias</hi> ſhould come with Miracles, they could not have had juſt reaſon to believe that Jeſus was the <hi>Chriſt,</hi> if he had not come with the Teſtimony of Miracles; ſo that they were neceſſary. But to deal plainly, they had not been ſufficient means of Conviction, if he had not alſo <hi>fulfilled the Law and the Prophets;</hi> becauſe the Law and the Prophets were to be fulfilled by him. For by an unqueſtionable Divine Revelation God had warned the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> not to truſt to mere Miracles. But after it had been foretold,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> xviii. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that <hi>God would raiſe up a Prophet from the midſt of that people like unto Moſes, to whom they ſhould heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en:</hi> After a Law had been given conſiſting of a vaſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Ordinances, which was to be a <hi>ſhadow of good things to come,</hi> and to be fulfilled in <hi>Chriſt:</hi> After that from time to time there were predictions of thoſe marks by which he ſhould be known; and amongſt other things it was foretold, that he ſhould work Miracles; when, I ſay, after all, <hi>Jeſus</hi> anſwered every one of theſe Characters, and did every way fulfil the Law and the Prophets; this all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was a demonſtration that he was the <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and as his Miracles, and the Miracles of his Apoſtles gave teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to him, and corroborated all other Divine Teſtimonies which he had; ſo they alſo received ſtrength from other
<pb n="xi" facs="tcp:65044:7"/> Divine Teſtimonies in conjunction with them; and in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, from thoſe very predictions that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould be known by Miracles, amongſt other things.</p>
            <p>No wonder therefore that we do not find the whole ſtreſs of the Divine Demonſtration of the Goſpel, laid upon the Miracles of Chriſt and his Apoſtles in the New Teſtament; and that tho our Saviour did appeal to his own works, yet not to them only, but likewiſe to the Scriptures of the Old Teſtament, and this rather more than to Miracles. Thus to fix the two doubting Diſciples that were going to <hi>Emaus,</hi> he upbraided them in this manner, <hi>O Fools,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> xxiv. 25 26, 17.</note> 
               <hi>and ſlow of heart to believe all that the Prophets have ſpoken; Ought not Chriſt to have ſuffered theſe things, and to enter into his Glory? And beginning at Moſes and all the Prophets, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded unto them in all the Scriptures the things concerning himſelf.</hi> This method was indeed ſuitable to the obligation that people were under, to examine all <hi>New</hi> Revelations by their correſpondence with the <hi>Old.</hi> And for this Reaſon, I make no doubt, but that our Saviour in his diſcourſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>All the Prophets</hi> had foretold concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Chriſt,</hi> did not omit to bring to their minds what Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles himſelf had wrought in the ſight of the people, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this would naturally fall under that head of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies which foretold that part of his Teſtimony. But then ſtill it was the Teſtimony of the old Scriptures, into which the Teſtimony of his Miracles was in great part reſolved: For there he laid the aggravation of their Incredulity, <hi>O Fools, and ſlow of heart to believe all that the Prophets have ſpoken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was foretold, That when God ſhould come to <hi>ſave</hi> them, <hi>The eyes of the blind</hi> ſhould be <hi>opened,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> xxxv. 4, 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>the ears of the deaf</hi> ſhould be <hi>unſtopped, the lame man</hi> ſhould <hi>leap as an hart, and the tongue of the dumb</hi> ſhould <hi>ſing.</hi> To which Predictions, our Saviour ſeemed to refer in that Anſwer
<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:65044:8"/> which he gave to the two Diſciples ſent by <hi>John the Baptiſt, Go,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> xi. 4, 5.</note> ſays he, <hi>and ſhew</hi> John <hi>again thoſe things which ye do hear and ſee; The blind receive their ſight, and the lame walk, and the lepers are cleanſed, and the deaf hear, and the dead are raiſed up.</hi> For beſides that there is no great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riation of the Phraſe from the words of the Prophet, there is another mark added, which had nothing in it of Miracle, <hi>viz. And the poor have the Goſpel preached to them;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> lxi. 1.</note> but then it was foretold by the Prophet, <hi>The Spirit of the Lord God is upon me, becauſe the Lord hath anointed me to preach good tidings unto the meek.</hi> This was in it ſelf a good mark no leſs than the other; but both received ſtrength from the Predictions of the Scripture. I make no queſtion, but that many believed in Jeſus chiefly for his Works ſake, before they had much conſidered the corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence of his Doctrine to <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets;</hi> but it ſeemeth alſo, that one reaſon of their forwardneſs was this, that they expected according to the Prophets, that he ſhould come with wonderful works: For thus we find in St. <hi>John,</hi> that the people who believed in him, ſaid, <hi>When Chriſt cometh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> vii. 31.</note> 
               <hi>will he do more Miracles than thoſe which this man hath done?</hi> In ſaying of which, they diſcovered an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of a <hi>Meſſias</hi> that ſhould work Miracles.</p>
            <p>Now when Chriſt came into the World, to fulfil all that had been foretold of him in the Scriptures, he indeed, and his Apoſtles after him, wrought ſuch Miracles, as without all queſtion had been ſufficient means of Conviction, if God had not thought fit to raiſe firſt, and then to anſwer the expectation of other Teſtimonies beſides Miracles. In a matter of this high concernment to mankind, he was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to give us Teſtimony upon Teſtimony, and not only the Teſtimony of Miracles added to others, but ſome ſuch Miracles too, as are in themſelves convincing; as that of Raiſing from the Dead. And we may boldly ſay, That
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:65044:8"/> God who has given us caution againſt Signs and Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, never yet ſuffered ſo great a temptation to happen, as that any one ſhould be raiſed from the Dead, in confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a falſe Doctrine; and this, notwithſtanding the bold ſtories of I know not how many, that have been ſaid to be raiſed from the Dead in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> But now as ſtrong an Argument as this is by it ſelf; yet St. <hi>Peter</hi> in his firſt Sermon to the <hi>Jews,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts ii. 22.</note> having obſerved that <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth</hi> was a <hi>man approved of God by Miracles, ſigns and wonders, which God had done by him in the midſt of them,</hi> and then proceeding to that moſt convincing ſign of all, <hi>viz.</hi> the Reſurrrection of <hi>Jeſus</hi> from the dead; he did not think fit to lay the whole ſtreſs upon the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing it ſelf, but produced that predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>David</hi> concerning it;<note place="margin">V. 25. Pſal xvi. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Thou wilt not leave my ſoul in hell, neither wilt thou ſuffer thy holy One to ſee corruption:</hi> And from this prediction of the thing he ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued induſtriouſly, as you may ſee, to prove that the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Reſurrection was a Divine Teſtimony; <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts ii. 31, 32.</note> ſays he, <hi>ſeeing this before, ſpake of the Reſurrection of Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. And then he affirms the Fact, and offers the proof of it; <hi>This Jeſus hath God raiſed up, whereof we all are wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame St. <hi>Peter</hi> affirming the reality of that miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous teſtimony which our Lord received in the Holy Mount, made no doubt to prefer the Teſtimony of the Scripture, before that Teſtimony; <hi>We have not,</hi> ſays he, <hi>followed cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly deviſed fables,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.16.17.18.</note> 
               <hi>when we made known unto you the coming and power of our Lord Jeſus, but were eye-witneſſes of his maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty; for he received from God the Father honour and glory, when there came forth ſuch a voice to him, from the excellent glory, This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well-pleaſed: and this voice which came from Heaven, we heard when we were with him in the Holy Mount.</hi> Now altho this was in it ſelf a
<pb n="xiv" facs="tcp:65044:9"/> very clear and convincing Teſtimony, yet St. <hi>Peter,</hi> who underſtood theſe things as well as any that have ſat in his Chair, rather refers <hi>Chriſtian</hi> people to the Teſtimony of the Scriptures, in thoſe remarkable words; <hi>We have alſo a more ſure word of Propheſie, whereunto ye do well that ye take heed, as unto a light ſhining in a dark place, until the day dawn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 19.</note> 
               <hi>and the day-ſtar ariſe in your hearts.</hi> Where the Old Teſtament is called a <hi>word of Propheſie,</hi> becauſe the great buſineſs of thoſe Holy Books was to prepare mankind for the coming of Chriſt, by all kinds of prediction: and now that Chriſt was come, if there remained any <hi>darkneſs</hi> or doubting in their minds, who had ſeen or known other Teſtimonies given to Jeſus, they were to <hi>take heed</hi> to the word of Propheſie, and diligently obſerve the correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the event to all things that had been foretold con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſt; in doing of which their doubts would by degrees vaniſh, and at laſt they would grow to a clear and ſtrong perſwaſion. And St. <hi>Peter</hi> therefore calls the word of Propheſie a <hi>ſure</hi> word, becauſe it is in it ſelf the beſt means to make us <hi>ſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor was this forgotten by St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in that Diſcourſe of which I have already cited ſome part;<note place="margin">De unit. Eccl. <hi>c. 16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Our Lord Jeſus him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> ſays he, <hi>after he had riſen from the dead, and when he expoſed his Body to be ſeen by the eyes, and felt by the hands of his Diſciples, leſt they ſhould think ſome Deceit was upon them, thought it more neceſſary, that they ſhould be confirmed by the Teſtimonies of the Law, and the Prophets, and the Pſalms, ſhewing that thoſe things which had been foretold ſo long before, were now fulfilled in Him.</hi> I ſhould unreaſonably exceed the bounds of ſuch a Preface as I deſigned at firſt, if I ſhould bring together thoſe Teſtimonies of Fathers more Ancient than St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> which run in this ſtrain. But I muſt make the more haſt, becauſe having ſaid thus much on the one ſide, concerning the Authority which the Miracles of
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:65044:9"/> Chriſt and his Apoſtles received, from their being foretold, and from all other Teſtimonies concurring with them; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I come to the other ſide, <hi>viz.</hi> in what caſe Miracles are not to be relied upon, I take my ſelf to be ſomething obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to ſhew what there is peculiar in the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of <hi>Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> and diſtinct from other Teſtimonies and Arguments of the Truth of Chriſtianity, and for which we have infinite reaſon to bleſs and to praiſe God, That our Religion is grounded upon <hi>Miracles,</hi> as well as upon the correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of both Teſtaments, upon Prophecies, and the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Temper and Deſign of the Doctrine of our Lord <hi>Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which I take to be peculiar to the Teſtimony of Miracles, is, that they make ſtrong Impreſſions upon the mind more ſuddenly than any other <hi>Arguments:</hi> When a thing is done, that is evidently above the courſe of Nature, it does not only raiſe Admiration, but ſets the thoughts a work concerning the reaſon and meaning of what is come to paſs. Miracles do arreſt and faſten the minds of men all at once, and forthwith engage them to conſider what God would inſtruct them in, by theſe ſupernatural effects of his Power and Preſence: If they do not preſently cauſe belief, yet they diſpoſe the mind to it preſently, and fix the atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in order to farther inſtruction; they make way into our minds whether we will or no; whereas other Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments do not penetrate, till we have made way for them, by comparing one thing with another, and by laying a great many things together, which it is not eaſy to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade men to do firſt of all, unleſs they are raiſed ſomething above the common pitch; and it is probable that many, even of theſe, had never engaged their abilities in the ſearch of Truth by the examination of other Arguments, if they had not been firſt awakened by <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Wonders,</hi> into a concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment about Divine Revelations. But for the generality of mankind, it is evident that Miracles are the arguments which
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:65044:10"/> lead them more ſuddenly and unavoidably than any other; for which reaſon St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> affirmed that the Doctrine of the <hi>Croſs</hi> made <hi>Ruſticks</hi> and ordinary perſons become <hi>Philoſophers:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſ.</hi> in 1 Cor. 2. <hi>Hom.</hi> 4, 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>the demonſtration by miraculous Works and Signs, is more manifeſt than that by Diſcourſes.</hi> And he prefers the ſhort way of the Apoſtles in making Converts, before the tedious methods of the Philoſophers in inſtructing their hearers, not only becauſe Miracles are a Divine Argument adapted to a Divine Revelation; but becauſe alſo they are adapted to the underſtanding of all ſorts of people, and God would have all men to come to the knowledg of the Truth.</p>
            <p>There is this then ſingular in the Teſtimony of Miracles, that they rouze the attention of the dulleſt; and if they do not at once both amaze and convince, yet they engage men to farther conſideration, and lead them to all other Arguments that are fit to be inquired into; in ſaying which, I believe I ſpeak to the ſenſe of all perſons that are acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the motives of Faith. When we firſt read the New Teſtament, they are the mighty works of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and of his Apoſtles there recorded, that firſt lay hold upon our minds, and command an earneſt attention; other Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations and Arguments come on by degrees. Thus alſo the Evangeliſts deſcribe the effect of thoſe Miracles which our Lord did; when he made the Blind to ſee, and the Dumb to ſpeak,<note place="margin">Matth. xii. 22, 23. Mark i. 22.</note> 
               <hi>All the people were amazed, and ſaid, Is not this the Son of David?</hi> And when he had <hi>caſt out an unclean ſpirit in the Synagogue, they were all amazed, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that they queſtioned among themſelves, ſaying, What thing is this? What new Doctrine is this? For with Authority he commandeth even the unclean ſpirits, and they obey him.</hi> Which are manifeſtly the words of men ſurprized with earneſt thoughts of a matter that they were little or nothing concerned about before, and who were
<pb n="xvii" facs="tcp:65044:10"/> now in the way of conſidering it farther, if they were not yet fully ſatisfied: For it is not to be doubted, but that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers were overwhelmed by the evidence of his mighty works, and yielded without much farther enquiry: But there were others again, whom the Miracles of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apostles</hi> had not brought to a full perſwaſion, but only raiſed in them a vehement deſire of farther ſatisfaction; and ſuch as theſe the <hi>Jews</hi> of <hi>Berea</hi> ſeemed to be,<note place="margin">Acts xvii. 11.</note> who <hi>were more noble than thoſe of Theſſalonica, in that they received the word with all readineſs of mind, and ſearched the Scriptures daily whether thoſe things were ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus far have I been carried away by the Argument, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond what I firſt deſigned; but I hope the Reader has not forgot, that this laſt Digreſſion concerning the ſingular Force of Miracles, was upon occaſion of the Third Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the Miracles of <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> on the one ſide, and the latter Miracles that are ſo much talked on, on the other, <hi>viz.</hi> That tho there was an admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition before-hand, not to truſt to Miracles at all adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; yet the <hi>Jews</hi> were made to expect Miracles from him who ſhould by all other Characters be known to be the <hi>Meſſias:</hi> And this we have ſpoken to already.</p>
            <p>Now on the other hand we alſo are fore-warned in the New Teſtament, to take <hi>heed</hi> that we be not deluded by <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Wonders;</hi> for it is foretold,<note place="margin">Matth. xxiv. 24.</note> That ſome ſhould <hi>ariſe,</hi> and <hi>ſhew great Signs and Wonders:</hi> And who are they that ſhould do ſo? Our Saviour tells us, that they are <hi>falſe Prophets;</hi> and therefore a man that runs after Miracles, may happen to fall into the hands of Deceivers: Well, but was there any alteration of the ſtate of Religion ſore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told, from what <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> left it? <hi>Moſes,</hi> we know, told the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> That God would raiſe up a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet like unto him, to whom they ſhould hearken in all things; and they had reaſon to expect a Prophet that
<pb n="xviii" facs="tcp:65044:11"/> ſhould make a great alteration in Religion, not by <hi>deſtroying,</hi> but by <hi>fulfilling</hi> the Law: This then I ask, Have we the like reaſon (or had our Fathers) to expect a Reformation of that ſtate of Religion which <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> left? Was any body to come after the Apoſtles, and to ſupply what was wanting in the Faith which they delivered to the Saints? Was it foretold that he or they who ſhould ariſe to make this Addition to the Doctrine of <hi>Christ,</hi> ſhould amongſt other marks, be known by the power of Miracles? If nothing of this can be ſhewn, as I am ſure nothing of it can, then we are under greater obligations than the <hi>Jews</hi> were, to beware leſt we be deceived by a noiſe of Miracles, nay though they be really <hi>Great Signs and Wonders:</hi> And though we have very great reaſon to rely upon the Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles, yet we have no reaſon at all to regard the Miracles of the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> For <hi>Chriſt</hi> was to come and make an alteration in the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> But neither was the Pope nor any body elſe to come and make an alteration in the Law of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> I know indeed, that the Scriptures fore-tell great changes would be made in the Chriſtian World; but they are not for the credit of thoſe that pretend to Miracles; St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that the <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſpeaketh expreſly, that in the latter times ſome ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> iv. 1.</note> 
               <hi>giving heed to ſeducing ſpirits,</hi> &amp;c. And he aſſureth us, that before the day of Judgment, there ſhall <hi>come a falling away,</hi> accompanied with <hi>power and ſigns, and lying wonders.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> ii. <hi>from</hi> v. 3. <hi>to</hi> v. 12.</note> Theſe predictions I ſuppoſe will not be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to encourage us to truſt new Miracles, but they give us ſome reaſon to ſtick to the old Religion, and then the old Miracles will ſerve our turn; and I think they make it very neceſſary to examine their Doctrine with a little more care, who pretend to Miracles, than if they pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to no ſuch thing.</p>
            <pb n="xix" facs="tcp:65044:11"/>
            <p>It pleaſed God to continue the power of Miracles in the Ancient Church for ſome time after the Apoſtles; and it may pleaſe him, for ought we know, to awaken the world again by Miracles; but whenever this happens, it will not be for the bringing in of new, but for the confirmation of old Doctrines. But as for thoſe that would recommend Doctrines to us which have neither Scripture nor Ancient Tradition for them, their Miracles are ſo far from proving them to be true, that they do but help to prove them falſe; becauſe it is foretold, that Deceivers ſhould uſe this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, That if an <hi>Angel from Heaven preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any other Goſpel</hi> than that which was preached at firſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> i. 8, 9.</note> he ſhould be <hi>Accurſed:</hi> Methinks <hi>Miracles</hi> ſhould not be able to recommend new Doctrine, any more than <hi>Angels from Heaven;</hi> eſpecially ſince we are not only forewarned againſt regarding <hi>Angels from Heaven,</hi> if they ſhould preach a new Faith, but likewiſe againſt regarding <hi>Miracles</hi> if they ſhould be done in confirmation of it; for as the believing <hi>Jews</hi> could ſay upon the Miracles of <hi>Christ</hi> and his Apoſtles, Now are thoſe Scriptures fulfilled, which fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told the Coming of the great Prophet with Miracles; ſo when we ſee (if we could ſee them) the Miracles that are ſaid to be wrought, for a Doctrine that has neither Scripture nor Fathers for it, but both againſt it, we muſt needs ſay, that the Scriptures are thereby fulfilled too, which foretold the coming of Deceivers with <hi>Great Signs</hi> and <hi>Wonders, and all deceivableneſs of unrighteouſneſs:</hi> And therefore now is the time to remember that neceſſary cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Lord, <hi>Behold I have told you before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude therefore, If we have good reaſon, as moſt undoubtedly we have, to believe a Doctrine that was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the moſt publick and unqueſtionable Miracles that ever were wrought, and which had all other concurrent Characters of a Divine Revelation; for ſuch is the Doctrine
<pb n="xx" facs="tcp:65044:12"/> of the Scriptures; then we have the ſame reaſon to reject thoſe latter Miracles that come to prove new Doctrines, becauſe God hath in the Holy Scriptures warned us againſt them; but there was no reaſon why the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhould have rejected the Miracles of <hi>Chriſt</hi> too; for they were told that he ſhould come working Miracles, and he had all other Divine Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and in all other reſpects he fulfilled the Scriptures, and anſwered the Characters of that Prophet, to whom they were to <hi>hearken in all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt now confeſs that I have purſued this Argument with great ſeriouſneſs, but without any great need for it in this place. One would now imagine that here follows a Collection of Stories moſt Wonderful and Convincing, and ſuch as might even ſhake the Faith of a ſimple man, and almoſt conſtrain him to believe Tranſubſtantiation, and to Adore the Hoſt: But I am of opinion that we might have ventur'd the Miracles and the Man together, without a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face; only I was willing to ſay ſomething not altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent to the Subject of the Book, that the entertainment here offered, might be as profitable to ſome, as I gueſs it will be pleaſant to moſt Readers.</p>
            <p>The Reverend Father, the Collector, being <hi>reſolved to ſend the Hereticks to School to the Beaſts, that</hi> (as he tells us in his Preface) <hi>they may become more wiſe, and return to their Reaſon, being taught by the Animals that have none,</hi> has alſo aſſured us, That <hi>this</hi> is the <hi>laſt Remedy.</hi> I ſuppoſe he means the laſt in the way of Reaſon, which happens to be true with us; for all other Remedies of this kind, ſuch as they are, have been tried upon us, and found in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual: And therefore 'tis now requiſite to to try the <hi>laſt,</hi> of going <hi>to School to the Beaſts,</hi> that <hi>we may return to our Reaſon, being taught by the Animals that have none.</hi> To which School we ſhould not be aſhamed to go, ſince we are ſent thither in very good Company, as well of <hi>grown
<pb n="xxi" facs="tcp:65044:12"/> and aged Catholicks,</hi> who are ſent to <hi>enkindle their zeal;</hi> as of Catholick <hi>Childron,</hi> upon whoſe <hi>minds the firſt Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief is to be imprinted,</hi> by putting <hi>theſe devout Hiſtories into their hands;</hi> which laſt is a good reaſon why we ſhould go to this <hi>School,</hi> and be put into the ſame Form with the Children, becauſe the <hi>Firſt Belief</hi> is yet to be <hi>Imprint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon our minds</hi> too. By all means therefore, let every one go to this School; and that no man who is come thus far, may be altogether Ignorant of the <hi>Leſſons</hi> that he is to learn, I do not care if I give him a ſample or two, out of the <hi>Liber Feſtivalis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There was an Erle of Venys was called Synt</hi> Ambrighte,<note place="margin">Lib. Feſti. de Corpore Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti.</note> 
               <hi>that loved the Sacrament in the Auter paſſing wele, and did hit all the worſhippe and reverence that he cowde and mighte; ſo whan that he lay ſyke and ſhulde be dede, he might not receyve the Sacrament for caſting; than was he ſorry and made Dole, and than he lette make clean his right ſyde, and to cover it with a fayre clothe of Sendell, and ley Goddis body thereon, And ſaid thus to the Oſte, Lord, thou knowiſte that I love the with all my hert, and would faine reſceive the with my mouthe, and I durſte, and thirfor that I may notte. I ley the on that place that is nexte to my herte, and ſo I ſhew the all the love of my herte that I can and may, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for y beſeche the good Lord have mercy on me. And even therwith, in ſighte of all the people that were aboute hym, his ſyde openyd, and the Oſte wente therin to his ſyde, and thanne his ſyde cloſed agin, and ſo anon after he dyde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>We Rede, that there was a Jewe that went with a Chriſten man, a felowe of his, into a Church of Chriſten people, and herde Maſſe; and after, when Maſſe was don, the Jewe ſeyde to the Chriſten man, yf I hadde eton as moche as thou haſt eton, I ſhulde not be an hungred, as I trow, in many daies. And thanne ſeyde Chriſten man, Forſouthe, quod he, I ete no mete this dey. Than ſeyde the Jew, I ſaw the ete a Child,
<pb n="xxii" facs="tcp:65044:13"/> the which the Preſte helde up at the Auter. Thanne come a fayre man that hadde many Children in his armys, and he gave eche Criſten a Childe, ſoch as the Preſte ete.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In</hi> Devynchire, <hi>beſyde</hi> Exbridge, <hi>was a Woman ley ſycke, and was nye dede, and ſente aftyr a hooly perſon abowte myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyghte, to have her rightes; Than this man in all the haſte that he myghte, he aroſe and wente to Churche, and toke God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis body in a Box of Yvory, and putte hit into his Boſome, and wente forth toward this Woman. And as he went thourgh a Foreſte in a fayr mede that was his next wey, it happid that his Box fill oute of his Boſome to the Grounde, and he wente forthe and woſſe hit not, and come to this Woman, and herde her Confeſſion. And than he asked her yf She wolde be Hoſiled, and She ſeyde, ye ſere; than he putte his honde in his Boſome, and ſought the Box, and when he founde hit noughte, he was full ſorry and ſadde, and ſeyde, Dame, I woll go aftyr Goddis body, and come anone agene to yow, and ſo went forthe ſore weping for his ſimpleneſs; and ſo as he come to a Welow Tree, he made therof a Rodde, and ſtrypped hymſelfe all nakyd, and ſo bete hymſelfe that the blode ranne downe by his ſyde, and ſeyde thus to himſelf, O thou ſimple man, why haſte thou loſte thy Lord God, thy Maker, thy For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and thy Creatour? And when he hadde thus bete hymſelf, he dede on his clothis and wente forthe. And thanne he was ware of Pilour of fyre that laſte from Erthe to Heven, and he was all aſtoyned therof, yet he bleſſed, and wente therto, and there ley the Sacrament fallyn oute of the Boxe into the Graſſe, and the Pilour ſchon as bryghte as any Sonne, and laſtyd from Goddis Body to Hevyn, and all the Beſtys of the Foreſte were come aboute Goddys Body, and ſtode in compaſs round aboute hit, and all knelid on foure knees, ſave on blacke Horſe that knelyd but on that on knee: Thanne ſeyde he, yf thow be any Beſte that may ſpeke, I charge the in Goddis name here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente in forme brede, tell me why thow kneliſte but on thy on
<pb n="xxiii" facs="tcp:65044:13"/> knee? Thanne ſeyde he, I am a fende of Hell, and wolle not kneel and y mighte, but y am made agenſe my will; for hit is wreton, that every knelying of Heven and of Erth ſhall be to the Lord God. Why art thou like a Horſe? And he ſeyde, to make the people to ſtele me; and at ſoche a Town was one hanged for me, and at ſoche a Town another. Thanne ſeyde this hooly perſon, Y commande the by Goddis Fleſche and his Blode, that thow goo into Wilderneſſe, and be ther as thow ſhalte never diſceſe Chriſten people more. And anone he wente his wey, he myghte no longer abyde: And thanne this man wente forthe to this woman, and dede her rightes, by the whiche ſhe was ſavid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which laſt Story is very much to the purpoſe of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Collection; and is ſingular in this, that here the Devil is brought in adoring the Hoſt againſt his will, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Beaſts that did it without any will at all.</p>
            <p>For the Tranſlation of this Book, I think the Gentlemen of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church have no reaſon to be offended with it, unleſs it be for this, that it is done a little out of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. They would I believe have done it themſelves in due time: For tho Divine Miracles are uſually the firſt means of Conviction, yet the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> reſerves them for the laſt; and then tries to make the people believe her Miracles, when they are made to believe every thing elſe beforehand. But ſince Miracles are for a ſign to them that believe not, why ſhould we not for once put them to the right uſe, and try how theſe will work upon our honeſt Countrymen? For which purpoſe they are to underſtand that theſe are not Old Wives Tales, nor <hi>made,</hi> however they may happen to be <hi>told,</hi> in Chimny Corners. The Story of the great Spider at St. <hi>Pauls</hi> is told by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelf: And ſo is that of St. <hi>Anthony</hi> of <hi>Padua</hi>'s Mule,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Sacr. Euch.</hi> lib. 3. c. 8.</note> which after three days faſting, left his Provender to worſhip
<pb n="xxiv" facs="tcp:65044:14"/> the Hoſt. And all of 'em, as the <hi>French</hi> Licenſe tells us, are collected out of Catholick Authors. And there is ſomething the leſs reaſon to queſtion the credibility of them, becauſe <hi>ſigns</hi> and <hi>wonders</hi> were to come one day, as we obſerved before.</p>
            <p>But we have now been long enough in the <hi>Porch,</hi> The <hi>School</hi> is opened; The Reverend Father invites all perſons to enter into it, both old and young, and <hi>Catholicks</hi> as well as <hi>Hereticks.</hi> I invite them too, making no doubt, <hi>of what the R. Father would fain hope,</hi> that ſome will come out a little wiſer than they went in.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:65044:14"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE H. Sacrament of the Altar, inſtituted in the Church, for the nouriſhing, inlightning, fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and comforting the Faithful, is one of the moſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime and Salutary Myſteries, that is to be found in the Catholick Religion. It ſtood in need alſo of a God, for to inſtitute it, and to propoſe it to us, as the ſtrongeſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the Love that he bore towards mankind. Which makes me aſtoniſh'd why the Hereticks ſhould conſpire with all their might for to extirpate it, conducted, no doubt, by the Devil, who pretend only to take away the belief and the uſe of it, ſo to deſtroy Souls more eaſily, who cannot ſubſiſt long in grace, without the participation of this Divine and Celeſtial Food. Wherefore without troubling my ſelf to confute theſe hair-brain'd People, who turn a deaf Ear to all that the Holy Fathers have ſaid about it, and have renounced their reaſon, I reſolved to ſend them to School to the Beaſts, who have ſhowed a particular inclination, not without a Superior conduct, for the Worſhip and Defence of this Truth. I have put my diſcourſe into an Alphabetical order, to the end that by this laſt remedy, they may become more wiſe, and return
<pb facs="tcp:65044:15"/> to their reaſon, being taught by the Animals, that have none. If they receive no benefit hereby no more than others, yet I hope it will be ſerviceable to Catholiques, to enkindle their Zeal, by a more careful frequenting this Bread of ſtrong men: and not only ſerve the grown and aged perſons, who have already a full belief and high eſteem for this Divine Sacrament; but alſo (which is one of my motives hereto) to imprint on the Minds of Children, the firſt belief, and a wiſe regard for this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, to the end that they may come to it, when they are judged capable to receive it, with more devotion and reverence.</p>
            <p>Which is that which I have ſeen put in practiſe by good Fathers of Families, who uſe to put into their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Hands, ſuch like Devout Hiſtories, to diſpoſe them to communicate worthily, when they firſt receive the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>It is alſo moſt certain, that Hiſtories and Examples, however it comes to paſs, have a great advantage to make impreſſions on the minds of Children, above diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes and reaſonings, which are above the capacities of youth.</p>
            <p>Note. <hi>Where the Engliſh word for Birds or Beaſts,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>agrees not to the Alphabetical order, I have ſet the French word in the Margin.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65044:15"/>
            <head>THE <hi>School of the Euchariſt,</hi> Eſtabliſhed upon The Miraculous Reſpects and Acknowledgments which Beaſts, Birds, and Inſects, upon ſeveral occaſions, have rendred to the H. Sacrament of the Altar, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="A" type="part">
               <head>A <hi>Abeilles,</hi> Bees.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>1.</hi> Bees honour the H. Hoſt divers ways, by lifting it from the Earth, and carrying it in their Hives as it were in Proceſſion.</head>
                  <p>A Certain Peaſant of <hi>Auvergne,</hi> a Province in <hi>France,</hi> perceiving that his Bees were likely to die, to prevent this misfortune, was advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, after he had received the Communion, to reſerve the Hoſt, and to blow it into one of his Hives. As he tryed to do it, the Hoſt fell on the ground. Behold now a wonder! On a ſudden all the Bees came forth out of their Hives, and ranging themſelves in good order, lifted the Hoſt up from the ground, and carrying it in upon their wings, placed it among their Combes. After this the man went out about his buſineſs, and at his return found that this adviſe had ſucceeded ill, for all his Bees were dead. Moreover when he lifted up the Hive, he ſaw that the Hoſt was turned into a fair Child among the Honey-Combes. Being much aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd at this change, and ſeeing that this Infant ſeemed to be dead, he took it in his hands, intending to bury it privately in the Church; but when he came to do it, he found nothing in his hands, for the Infant was vaniſh'd and gone. This thing happened in the County of <hi>Clermont,</hi> which, for this irreverence, was a while after chaſtiſed by divers cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, which ſo diſpeopled thoſe parts, that they became like a Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs. <hi>Pet. Cluniac. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:65044:16"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>2.</hi> Bees adore the H. Hoſt, and ſing the Divine Praiſes, dividing themſelves into two Quires.</head>
                  <p>IT is reported of another poor man, that going to viſit his Bees, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived them to make a ſweet harmony; he ſtood raviſhed a while with it, not knowing what it meant. The night following as he went out about ſome buſineſs, and caſt his Eyes towards his Bees, he perceiv'd them to rejoyce, and ſport themſelves, making an admirable me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody. He firſt inform'd his Curate of it, and afterwards the Biſhop, who after they had conſulted about it, adviſed him to break up the Hive, where they found a Box or Pix made of Wax, but of ſuch whiteneſs, that it looked like Ivory, and within it the H. Sacrament adored by the Bees, who ranged themſelves into two Quires, and ſang the praiſes of their Creator. The Biſhop gave order for a goodly Proceſſion, to carry back the H. Hoſt to the Church; and in that place was erected a fair Chappel, which became a place of refuge for the ſick and afflicted. When no body knew from whence and by whom that Hoſt had been brought thither, two Thieves of their own accord diſcovered themſelves and confeſſed, that having ſtollen a Pix, they had thrown the Hoſt againſt the Hives. <hi>Cantiprat. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 40. <hi>ſec.</hi> 1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>3.</hi> Bees erect a compleat Chappel with their Wax.</head>
                  <p>A Certain Woman as covetous as the former Peaſant, having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Communion unworthily, carried the Hoſt to her Hives for to enrich her Stock of Bees; and afterwards coming again thither to underſtand the Succeſs, ſhe perceived that the Bees acknowledging their God in the Sacrament, had with admirable Artifice erected to him a Chappel of Wax, with its Dores, Windows, Bells, and Veſtrie, and within it a Chalice where they layd the H. Body of Jeſus Chriſt. She could not long conceal this wonder: The Prieſt being advertiſed of it, came thither in Proceſſion, and he himſelf heard a conſort of moſt har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious Muſick, which the Bees made flying round about the H. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament; and having taken it out, he brought it back to the Church full of comfort, certifying that he had ſeen and heard our Lord acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged and praiſed by thoſe little Animals. <hi>Caeſarius l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>4.</hi> They revenge the injuries done to the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>A Peaſant, ſwayed by a Covetous mind, being communicated on <hi>Eaſter-day,</hi> received the Hoſt in his Mouth, and afterwards laid it among his Bees, believing that all the Bees of the Neighbourhood would
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65044:16"/> come thitherto work their Wax and Honey. This covetous impious wretch, was not wholly diſappointed of his hopes; for all his Neighbours Bees come indeed to his Hives, but not to make honey, but to render there the honours due to the Creator. The iſſue of their Arrival was, that they melodiouſly ſang to him Songs of praiſe as they were able; after that they built a little Church with their Wax from the foundations to the roof, divided into 3 Rooms, ſuſtained by Pillars with their Baſes and Chapiters. They had there alſo an Altar, upon which they had laid the pretious Body of Jeſus Chriſt, and flew round about it, continuing their Muſique. The Peaſant who took notice of all this, though he could not comprehend the meaning of this harmony, yet was right glad to ſee all his neighbours Bees met together there. When the time came to examine what profit he had made, then it appeared how he was deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For when he would take a view of the quantity of honey and wax, which all theſe Swarms had made, he found all his hives empty of both; and coming nigh that hive where he had put the H. Sacrament, the Bees iſſued out furiouſly by Troops, and ſurrounding him on all ſides, revenged the irreverence done to their Creator, and ſtung him ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely, that they left him in a ſad caſe. This puniſhment made this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable wretch come to himſelf; who acknowledging his Error, went to find out his Pariſh Prieſt, to confeſs his fault to him. The Prieſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed the Biſhop about it, who adviſed him to go in proceſſion with all his Pariſhioners. At his Arrival the Bees teſtifyed the joy they had by their hummings, they came forth, and raiſed themſelves into the Ayr, making an excellent Melody. When they lifted up the Hive, they found that artful fabrick, where they ſaw upon the Altar the H. Body of our Lord, which they carried back with reverence and great cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to the Church, ſinging the praiſes of the Lord, who ſhould be more honoured and reverenced by men, ſince he had honour from theſe little Animals. <hi>Vincentius in ſpec. moral. l.</hi> 2. <hi>diſt.</hi> 21. <hi>p.</hi> 3.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Agneau,</hi> Lambe.</note>
                     <hi>1. A</hi> Lamb of St. <hi>Francis</hi> makes ſigns to a Lady to go to Maſſe.</head>
                  <p>ST. <hi>Francis</hi> had at <hi>Rome</hi> a Lamb that uſed to be preſent at Maſſe and Divine Service; and when the Saint went from thence, he recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended it to a Noble Lady, whom the Lamb awaked amornings by its bleating, when ſhe forgot to go to Maſſe, and ſignified to her by ſigns that ſhe ſhould go to Church. <hi>S. Bonav. in vit. S. Francis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:65044:17"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>2.</hi> A Lamb of St. <hi>Coleta</hi> kneeled at the Elevation during the Maſſe.</head>
                  <p>THE Humility and Sweetneſs of St. <hi>Coleta</hi> was ſuch, that the Birds of Heaven were emulous to ſing in her preſence, and came to feed at her Table: for this quality ſhe accepted a Lamb, which one made a preſent of to her, as a meek ſimple Animal, and alſo becauſe in the old Law it was offered in Sacrifice, repreſenting Jeſus Chriſt the Lamb with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Spot. She took ſo much pleaſure in this little Animal, that ſhe made it go with her to Church, as the Sheep of St. <hi>Francis</hi> uſed to doe) where without making any noiſe it behaved it ſelf with great modeſty and reverence and when the Prieſt that Officiated came to the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration, the little Lamb bended its knees, without ſtirring till the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation was over. <hi>Surius ad</hi> 6. <hi>Martii.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aragnee,</hi> A Spider.</note>
                     <hi>1.</hi> A Spider do's not at all impoyſon at the Maſſe: What happened to one of the Ciſtertion Order, to St. <hi>Conrade</hi> and St. <hi>Norbert.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Religious perſon of the Ciſtertian Order, celebrating the Maſſe, in the preſence of his Abbot <hi>Walenus,</hi> a Spider fell into the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated Chalice. Upon his doubting whether he ſhould drink the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated Wine, his Abbot commanded him to proceed and he in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience took and finiſhed all with great courage, and with fervor and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion. At his return being among his Brethren, his finger itched, he rubb'd it, and then a ſwelling appeared; and after that before them all, this Spider opened the Skin and came out alive, and by the Abbots com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand was burnt. <hi>Henriquez. in faſcic. S.S. Ciſterc. l.</hi> 2. <hi>diſt.</hi> 26.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>2.</hi> Another inſtance to the ſame purpoſe.</head>
                  <p>ST. <hi>Conrade</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtance</hi> ſwallowed a Spider, that fell into the conſecrated Wine. They that knew what he had done, looked every moment for his death, but it happened, quite otherwiſe. The Biſhop ſate down at Table, but eating nothing, one asked him the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he anſwered, that he waited for his Hoſt, who would come preſently; and leaning his head upon the Table, and opening his mouth, the Spider immediately iſſued out. This is what our Saviour had ſaid in St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> That if his Diſciples ſhould drink poiſon, it ſhould not hurt them at all. <hi>Surius</hi> 26. <hi>November. Corbin. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 497.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:65044:17"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>3.</hi> Another like the former.</head>
                  <p>ONe day as St. <hi>Norbert</hi> ſaid Maſſe in a Chappel underground, a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der fell into the Chalice already conſecrated. <hi>Norbert,</hi> that he might loſe nothing of what was there, ſwallowed it. When the Maſſe was done, as he was preparing himſelf for an unaviodable death, he found a great inclination to ſneez; and though he look'd upon this as a ſign of death, yet he found that to him it was a ſign of Life; For this Animal came out alive at his Noſtrils. A miraculous Effect, which ſo increaſed his faith, that it is a common ſaying now-a-days; the Faith of <hi>Norbert,</hi> the Charity of <hi>Bernard,</hi> and the Humility of <hi>Milon Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Teroanne. The Biſhop of</hi> Bellay <hi>in his Life.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>4.</hi> A Spider revenges an affront done to the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THomas</hi> of <hi>Arundel,</hi> being aſſembled with other Prelates in the Church of St. <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> to labour the converſion of a Taylor, who held that the conſecrated Hoſt, was onely bread bleſſed, and not at all the Body of Jeſus Chriſt; When after many diſputes they found him obſtinate in his Hereſy, he was commanded abſolutely to ſubmit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and to adore God with all reverence in the H. Sacrament. Upon the oppoſition that he made there even as far as to blaſpheme, ſaying, that a Spider rather deſerved to be honoured than the H. Sacrament of the Altar. Heaven revenged this ſaying ſo outragious againſt his God: for immediately an old overgrown Spider unlooſing it ſelf from the roof of the Church, came down by the guidance of its thread, upon this ſtinking curſed mouth, where being entred, he was grievouſly torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, anſwerably to that in the Proverbs, c. 6. <hi>Thou art inſnared in the words of thy mouth.</hi> After this, all judged him to deſerve death, and in concluſion he was condemned to be burnt, which ſentence was executed in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Chancellour of the Kingdom, in the year 1384. <hi>Bredek.</hi> 1. 30. <hi>Tho. Walden l. contr. Joannem Wicklef. &amp; alii.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aſnes,</hi> Aſſes.</note>
                     <hi>1.</hi> Aſſes honour the H. Sacrament, making way for a Prieſt that carried it.</head>
                  <p>AN Old and Simple Prieſt of the Pariſh of St. <hi>James</hi> at <hi>Colen,</hi> carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Holy Sacrament out of Town to a Sick Perſon, and going up a very rough Hill, met ſome loaded Aſſes, deſcending towards the Town, which often joſtled him, by reaſon of the narrowneſs of the way. At length not being able to get before them, and fearing to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned by thoſe Beaſts, he ſpake to them according to his ſimplicity in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65044:18"/> this manner: My Aſſes, what do you mean? do ye not ſee him whom I carry? go aſide and ſtop, to make more room for your Creator, which I command you in his name. O admirable Obedience! thoſe Aſſes, which uſed not to ſtir but when they are beaten, preſently went on one ſide, where the Hill was more ſteep without apprehending any danger, or letting fall their load. The Town of <hi>Collen</hi> remembers this wonder to this day, and mentions it with aſtoniſhment. <hi>Caeſarius l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 99.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>2.</hi> Another ſuch like Story.</head>
                  <p>IN the 16 Century within the <hi>Venetian</hi> territories, a Prieſt carrying the H. Sacrament without Pomp or Train, to a ſick perſon, he met out of the Town Aſſes going to their Paſture; who perceiving by a certain Sentiment, what it was the Prieſt carried, they divided themſelves into two Companies on each ſide the way, and fell upon their knees. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Prieſt with his Clerk all amazed, paſſed between thoſe peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Beaſts, which then roſe up, and, as if they would make a pompous ſhow in honour of their Creator, followed the Prieſt as far as the Sick mans houſe, where they ſtayed at the door, till the Prieſt came forth, whom they did not leave till he had given them his bleſſing. Father <hi>Simon Rodriguez,</hi> one of the firſt companions of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> who travelled then in this part of <hi>Italy,</hi> informed himſelf carefully of this matter, that it happened a little while before our Firſt Fathers came into <hi>Italy,</hi> and found that all had happened as has been told. <hi>P. Orlandin.</hi> in his Hiſt. of the Society. <hi>tom.</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 27.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>3.</hi> Another admirable Hiſtory of what happened, not to an Aſſe, but to a man turned into an Aſſe.</head>
                  <p>A Certain Knight of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> arriving at the Town of <hi>Famaguſta</hi> in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> with ſome others of the ſame Order, as they were buſied to provide themſelves of things neceſſary for the finiſhing their Voyage, this Knight went abroad, and walking along by the Sea ſide, he accoſted a Woman, and asked her whether ſhe had any Eggs to ſell. She, that was another <hi>Medea</hi> in Sorcery, ſeeing him young, luſty, and a ſtranger, that the Country people might ſuſpect nothing, deſired him to wait a while, and ſhe would furniſh him with every thing he want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. As ſhe tarried ſomewhat longer than he would have had her, ſo her fear leſt the Pilot ſhould not leave him aſhore, cauſed her to make more haſt: So ſhe brought him the Eggs, and told him, that if the Ship was gone, and he would come back to her, he ſhould be welcome. With this proviſion he drew towards his Ship, and ſeeing that his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65044:18"/> were not yet come, he fell to eating his Eggs. As he was eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, to his admiration, he found himſelf wholly altered, and that he went as it were out of himſelf, ſo that in an hours time he became dumb, and as if he had loſt his Brains (ſo he expreſt it after he was well) not knowing whence this happened. Moreover, when it was time to ſet Sail, he drew towards the Ship to take his place there, but was dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven away by great blows of a Staff, ſince he was changed into an Aſſe. He ſuſpected now ill dealing, and that this Woman had bewitched him, hearing them call him Aſſe; notwithſtanding though he could not make anſwer being dumb, yet he made another attempt to get into the Ship, but was treated juſt as before, being repulſed as an Aſſe by the ſtroaks of a good Cudgel. Being thus abandon'd by all, he was forced to go back to that Womans houſe, whom he ſerved as an Aſſe, for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of his life, the ſpace of 3 years, this Witch making uſe of him to carry proviſions to the Houſe: at 3 years end this poor young man following the Sorcereſs at a little diſtance, comming into the Town in ſhape of an Aſſe, by good chance, paſſing by a Church, he heard the Bell ring for the Elevation of the Hoſt; and preſently he turned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Church; but not having the hardineſs to go in, fearing to be driven away, he ſtaid without bending his knees and leggs towards the ground, and raiſing his head, bowed it to adore the H. Sacrament. This being obſerved by ſome Merchants of <hi>Genoa,</hi> and being greatly aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd, they followed this Aſſe, which a Woman drove away with a Cudgel, and went after them both as far as to the houſe. Hereupon, they advertiſed the Judge of the Town concerning this matter, who cauſed both the Aſſe and Woman to be apprehended. She being exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, confeſſed her crime, and promiſed the Judge, that if he would ſuffer her to go home, ſhe would reſtore the young Knight to his former ſhape, which ſhe did: As for her, ſhe was afterwards condemned to the fire and burnt for a Witch. <hi>Nic. de Laghi p.</hi> 244. <hi>&amp; Hier. Mengi de arte Exorciſticâ.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="B" type="part">
               <head>B.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Biche,</hi> A Hind.</note>
                     <hi>1.</hi> Hinds come to Maſſe on a H. Martyrs day, and make an offering of a young Cheverel.</head>
                  <p>ST. <hi>Athenogenes,</hi> a Martyr, under the Emperour <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> whoſe feaſt is kept on the 16th of <hi>July,</hi> returning to his Monaſtery, found none there ſave a Hind (the Monks being before laid in Priſon) which he had a long time nouriſht. She preſenting her ſelf before him and moving his Compaſſion, he bleſſed her, and prayed God, that ſhe might
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65044:19"/> never be taken nor fall into the Hunters nets, neither ſhe, nor her young ones: Charging her further, that ſhe and others of them ſhould yearly bring a Cheverel to the Monaſtery, to perpetuate the memory of this favour and priviledge. All came to paſs as the Martyr had required: for every year, after the reading of the Goſpel at the time of celebrating the Maſſe of the H. Martyr, they ſaw a Hind enter into the Church, and after ſhe had offered a Cherevel to the Saint, went back into the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts: It was ordained that this Cheverel ſhould ſerve for the feaſting the Prieſts that had celebrated the Office on the day of that Feaſt. <hi>Raderus Viridarii SS. p.</hi> 1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Boeufs,</hi> Oxen.</note>Oxen adore the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>CErtain Robbers broke into a Church of a Town called <hi>Homel,</hi> ſiez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon a Casket, in which they found nought beſides ſome reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques, and the Pix, in which they kept the H. Sacrament. But this booty not turning much to their profit, they left all in the Fields. In the morning before day, a Peaſant went out with his Oxen to plow; the Oxen being yoked in the plough, began to draw; but when they were come to the place where the H. Pix lay, they ſtopt on a ſuddain; the Peaſant, not knowing what was the matter, cryed to them aloud, and puſh'd them with his Staff to make them go forward, but all in vain. He increaſed his blows and his noyſe to no purpoſe, onely that he receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their kicks, they having more regard to the H. Sacrament, than to their Patron. The Peaſant in great anger left his plow, to look whether any thing was there which might cauſe this ſtop. As he did this, he took notice of that Pix lying at the feet of his beaſts, with the Relicks belonging to his Village. Being in a great aſtoniſhment, he left the field and his plough, to advertiſe the Pariſh-Prieſt of what he had found. Upon this report the Prieſt came out in proceſſion with the people to the place where the Hoſt and the H. Relicks lay, which they carried back to the Church with the ſame devotion; where they put them under a more ſafe Cuſtody. <hi>Caeſarius l.</hi> 9. 7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>2.</hi> Another ſtory to the ſame purpoſe.</head>
                  <p>IN <hi>Bavaria</hi> not far from <hi>Ingolſtad,</hi> a Peaſant who was a ſimple but devout man, not being able on all Feſtivals to be preſent at Maſſe; becauſe he was obliged to look after his Cattel, put a part of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated Hoſt, which he had reſerved, into a hole made in his Staff, which when he could not go to Church, he always fixed in the ground,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65044:19"/> and addreſſed his prayers to it, adoring the H. Sacrament. Now one time, as he ſaw his beaſts run about hither and thither, and would fain ſtop them, he heedleſly threw down his Staff, where the H. Sacrament was: But preſently reflecting upon what he had done, ran in great haſte to take it up: As he fell on his knees to do it, he ſaw that the ground, where his ſtaff was, depreſſed it ſelf, and ſo much the more, as he lift up his hand. This wonder troubled him, and ſtill more, when riſing up, he ſaw all the Oxen round about the hollow place, with bended knees adoring our Lord. Upon the ſight of theſe wonders, he ran bitterly weeping to give an account thereof to his Pariſh-Prieſt: He addreſſed himſelf to the Biſhop, who came thither in Proceſſion, and with great reverence and humility took up the Staff, in which was the Holy Sacrament. In memory of this Miracle, he built a Chappel under the Title of <hi>Saviour.</hi> A world of people came thither and took of the Earth of this hollow place in teſtimony of their Devotion. <hi>R. P. Lucas Pinelli at the end of his Meditat. on the Myſtery of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Brebis,</hi> A Sheep.</note>
                     <hi>4.</hi> A Sheep kneels at the Maſſe, at the Elevation of the Conſecrated Hoſt.</head>
                  <p>AT St. <hi>Mary de Portiuncula</hi> one gave S. <hi>Francis</hi> for an Almes a live Ewe, which he willingly received as a Symbol of innocence and ſimplicity. He admoniſhed her to live in the Convent without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieting the Friers; when the Friers went to the Quire, this Ewe went into the Church, and kneeled before the Altar of our Lady bleating, as if ſhe would ſalute her; and at the Elevation of the moſt H. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at the Maſſe, ſhe kneeled in token of adoration. S. <hi>Bonavent. in vit. S. Franciſci.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="C" type="part">
               <head>C.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cannes,</hi> Ducks.</note>
                     <hi>1.</hi> Ducks are preſent at Maſſe on St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> day. <hi>May 9.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THere is in the Suburbs of <hi>Monfort</hi> in <hi>Brittanie,</hi> a Pariſh Church of St. <hi>Nicholas,</hi> and at a little diſtance from thence one may ſee a Lake not far from a Caſtle of that Territory. From that Lake, for more than a hundred or 200 years, came forth a Wild Duck; which on St. <hi>Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las</hi> day, 9th of <hi>May</hi> came into this Church with a number of Ducklins, and among the people there aſſembled to the number of three or four
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65044:20"/> thouſand perſons, choſe its way and entred the Church, and abode there ſome while, without being frighted, and afterwards returned peaceably to its Lake. Some years ſince it did the ſame, but more ſeldom, and not every year. As a Lord of the Country whoſe name was <hi>Dandelot,</hi> who was of the New Religion, related this as a contrivance of ſome Prieſt; one day dining in this Town of <hi>Monfort,</hi> this Wild-Dack came thither, as if ſhe had a mind to appear to this man of a falſe perſwaſion; who being advertiſed of it came in Querpo, and running with ſome of his company to the ſaid Church, he beheld that Duck enter in, and after ſome while returned quietly thither from whence ſhe came: He fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed her by his Eye as far as to the Lake; after which when any one ſpoke of this Duck, he ſaid not a word. <hi>If theſe hold their peace the ſtones will cry out. Le Seur de Argentré in his Hiſtory of</hi> Brittain, <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 63, 64. <hi>Joh. Bapt. Fulgoſ. l. de Mirac.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>2.</hi> Young Ducks defend the Church, and puniſh Offenders till they make reparation for the wrongs they had done.</head>
                  <p>IN the Lake of <hi>Lagenne</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> one may ſee young Ducks among thoſe Ducks of S. <hi>Coleman,</hi> that had been made tame in his time, which were not afraid when men came nigh them. Theſe Ducklins that met together in this Lake about the number of ſixteen, conſtantly when any injury was done to the Church where the H. Sacrament was lodged, or to the Clergy, they forſook this Lake, and flew far away to another, and returned not till ſatisfaction was given, and reparation made of the wrong done to the Church and Clergy. And during their abſence, that the reparation might not be deferred, the Waters of that firſt Lake which were cleer and chryſtaline, became muddy and corrupt, and ſmelt ſo ill, that they became neither fit for the uſe of Men or Beaſts. The ſame Author alſo reports, that if any ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure one of the Birds, for being Protectors and Defenders of the Church, he would not eſcape long unpuniſhed. He reports that a Kite having caught up in his Tallons one of theſe Ducklins, perched upon a Tree to devour it; but immediately all his Members became ſtiffe, ſo that he could not perceive the prey under his feet. Another time in a Winter Froſt, a Fox caught one of theſe Birds but he had better have let it alone; for in the morning he was found in a Grot nigh to the Lake (venerable for the abode of S. <hi>Coleman</hi> there) dead and choaked; the Duck that he had in his throat ſtopping his breath. <hi>Nieremberg ex Sylveſt. Gyrald. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Mirac. in Europa.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:65044:20"/>
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cerf,</hi> A Stag.</note>A Stag traces the Circuit and the place of the Church of <hi>Noſtre Dame du Puy,</hi> at <hi>Velay</hi> in <hi>France.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN the days of S. <hi>George,</hi> the firſt Biſhop and Apoſtle of <hi>Velay,</hi> a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of that Country, who had a long time been ſick of a Quartan Ague, one day as ſhe was aſleep, heard this voice; Betake thy ſelf to the Rock <hi>d' Anis,</hi> this is the place where I will cure thee: She obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this voice, found there a large and ſquare Stone like an Altar. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeated there upon it, ſleep ſurprized her, and at the ſame time the Virgin appeared to her, ſaying to her at her awaking, Thou ſhalt be cured, and know that I have choſe this place to be honoured there in Ages to come. All which coming to paſs as had been foretold her, ſhe made a rehearſal of it to St. <hi>George,</hi> who went upon this Rock, where he was further aſſured of the Virgins pleaſure by a new Prodigy: for having attained to the top of the Mountain, he ſaw at the foot of the Rock <hi>de Corneille,</hi> the place where now our Ladies Church ſtands, all covered with Snow, though this was on the 11th of <hi>July.</hi> At the ſame time a Stag ſuddenly leapt forward in the Snow, took a round, as it were tracing the circuit and compaſs of the Church, which was there to be built, and having done this, diſappeared from the ſight of all that were preſent. S. <hi>George,</hi> proſtrating himſelf on the ground, to adore the traces of the Divine Providence, immediately ordained, that following the prints of the Stags feet, the place ſhould be encompaſſed with a ſtrong hedge, ſo that it might not be profaned, that ſince it could not be yet undertaken, it might be deferred to a better ſeaſon. S. <hi>George</hi> therefore contented himſelf with marking out the place for the Church, and other Prelates that ſucceeded him, had not the hardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to undertake the building, till S. <hi>Voſſi</hi> was eſtabliſht Biſhop there, who gave beginning to the Church, by reaſon of the Miracle follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. In his days a Lady of a very noble Family of <hi>Polignac,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing troubled with the Palſey, was advertiſed in her ſleep by the Virgin, that if ſhe would be healed, ſhe ſhould go up to the Mountain called <hi>Puy d' Anis,</hi> and there repoſe her ſelf upon a Stone made in the faſhion of an Altar: Being ſeated upon this Stone, ſhe fell there aſleep, till ſuch time as ſhe was awaked by an Angel: At her waking, ſhe ſaw the Mother of God ſurrounded with a great company of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Virgins, and at her feet ſhe lay proſtrate; the Virgin advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her to return thanks to her Son for the health that was reſtored to her, and to let the Biſhop know, that it was her pleaſure they ſhould build a Church in that place for the invocation of her holy name, and that he ſhould tranſlate thither the Epiſcopal See of <hi>Velay,</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:65044:21"/> according to the advice ſhe had given to S. <hi>George</hi> his Predeceſſor. This being reſolved, S. <hi>Voſſi</hi> went to <hi>Rome</hi> to get a Licenſe from the Pope, where he arrived in the year 224. S. <hi>Calixtus</hi> who governed then, received him courteouſly, and agreeing to his requeſts, gave him an Architect called <hi>Scutaire</hi> for to manage the work: The Temple was in a ſhort time finiſht and erected with great firmneſs and perfection: When the debate was about conſecrating it, the holy Biſhop conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that he had no Relicks, he concluded that he would return to <hi>Rome</hi> with <hi>Scutaire</hi> for to obtain them of the H. Father. The Evening before they went away, they took leave of the people, and made faſt all the Church doors; the day following when they were near the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Loize,</hi> a quarter of a League from the Town, they met two vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable old men. S. <hi>Voſſi</hi> approaching them, demanded of them whither they were going, and what brought them into thoſe quarters: They an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, We are Embaſſadors from the H. Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſent to Biſhop <hi>Vaſſi,</hi> to beſtow on him theſe two ſmall Caskets full of holy Relicks. The H. Biſhop gave them thanks, and intreated them that he might carry them up to the Mountain: They anſwered, that they had no intention to paſs any further, and at parting when they had delivered to them the Relicks with the Breviates, yet further to confirm them in the truth of all they had ſaid, Know, ſay they, that when you ſhall arrive at the Church gates, which you have firmly barred, they will open to you of themſelves; and you ſhall find in the Church three hundred and twelve lighted Torches, the Altar anointed and marked with Holy Oyle, and you ſhall alſo hear the harmonious Songs of Angels, and perceive a moſt ſweet Odour. Upon this they diſappeared; at their return to the Town the people had notice to be ready for a Proceſſion, and the H. Biſhop barefoot and in his Pontifical Habits, came with the people to Church, which as ſoon as they approached, the doors opened of themſelves; the Church was lightned with three hundred and twelve Torches, with all the other circumſtances marked by the two old men. The Biſhop approached to the Altar, which he found anointed with H. Oyl, upon which he placed the Holy Relicks. After they had ſolemnly ſung the Maſſe of Dedication, he publiſhed and declared by the Authority of our H. Father the Pope, that the Epiſcopal See was from thenceforth tranſlated, from the Old Town of <hi>Velay,</hi> to the New place, now called <hi>d' Anis,</hi> and in Latine <hi>Anicium,</hi> which is one of the moſt illuſtrious and ancient Churches of our Lady, that is in Europe. <hi>P. Odo Giſſe, in his Hiſtory of our Lady</hi> du Puy.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:65044:21"/>
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chenilles,</hi> Caterpillars.</note>
                     <hi>3.</hi> Caterpillars revenge the injury done to the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>A Prieſt exorciſing one that was poſſeſſed, demanded of the Devil, why a woman whoſe name was <hi>Hardifa,</hi> had been ſo grievouſly tormented by him; She has well deſerved it, replied he, for ſhe hath ſowed the moſt High upon her Coleworts. The Prieſt not knowing what this meant, and the Devil denying to give him any other anſwer, he went to that other poſſeſſed perſon called <hi>Hardifa,</hi> and told her the anſwer the Devil had made him, which he did not at all underſtand. I underſtand it well, ſays <hi>Hardifa,</hi> which yet I have never told to any Soul living. You muſt know then, ſaid ſhe, that being very young, I took upon me to look to the garden, and making no profit of it, becauſe Caterpillars devoured all the herbs, I learnt afterward of a wandring woman, that for to remedy this I muſt break a conſecrated Hoſt in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſcatter them upon the herbs, and they would ſpring up again: I did ſo, ſaid ſhe, but to my own harm, as you ſee. Behold here what the Devil meant, when he ſaid; She ſowed the moſt High upon her herbs. <hi>Caeſarius. l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cheval,</hi> A Horſe.</note>
                     <hi>4.</hi> A Horſe given to a Prieſt that carried the H. Sacrament to a ſick perſon.</head>
                  <p>WE will give the firſt place to a Horſe of <hi>Ralph</hi> Count <hi>de Haſpurg,</hi> and afterwards Emperour. This Prince going a Hunting heard the little Bell ring, as the Prieſt went with the H. Sacrament to a Sick perſon. He thereupon turned back to meet the Prieſt, and being come up to him, he lighted from his horſe, and preſented him to the Prieſt, that he might paſs over a Ford of the River, himſelf following on foot. When he had communicated the ſick Perſon, the Prieſt returned a horſeback to his Church, the Prince going all the while a foot. The Prieſt paying due reſpects thanked Count <hi>Ralph,</hi> and offered to return him his horſe. God forbid, ſaid the Prince, that I ſhould profane the horſe, which God has thus far conſecrated by the Service he has done him; My horſe, ſaid he, belongs to God, and I give him to the Church. When he had made this donation that the Church might not be burden'd with the neceſſary charges for his keeping, the Prince ſetled a certain revenue, to pay for the horſes keeping, and he made it perpetual, as well for the providing horſe-meat, as for the purchaſing another horſe, when he ſhould fail, for the Service of the Church. <hi>P. Gualterus Paulus in ſuis de Euch. Rithmis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:65044:22"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>5.</hi> A Jews Horſe pays reſpect to a Prieſt, who went with the H. Sacrament to a ſick perſon.</head>
                  <p>A Prieſt carrying the H. Sacrament, met a Jew on horſeback, who endeavouring to get before, his beaſt kneeled down bowing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the H. Sacrament. The Jew being in great diſorder ſlackned his Rein, and Spurred him hard. But his horſe would not ſtir till the Prieſt was gone by. At the ſame time he heard a voice from Heaven which ſaid, <hi>Acknowledge thy Creator, whom thou denyeſt to be born of the Virgin Mary.</hi> The Jew making reflexion upon this foregoing action of his horſe, and this divine Voice, was converted and baptized. <hi>Prompt. Diſc. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empl.</hi> 32.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>6.</hi> A Horſe ſignifies to his Maſter, that he ſhould hear Maſſe, before he went about his affairs.</head>
                  <p>A Perſon that was hard put to it to diſpatch certain affairs, was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted by ſome Clergy-men, becauſe it was Sunday, to hear Maſſe, before he took his journey; he went indeed to Church to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at Maſſe, but through his earneſt deſire to diſpatch his affairs, he went away before it was ended. He came home and got on horſe-back; but when he was upon going, his horſe would not ſtir either for beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or ſpurring. This unuſual obſtinacy of his horſe, made the Maſter conſider with himſelf; upon this he alights, returns to Church, and heard a Maſſe from the beginning to the end. Ater which he got again on horſeback, and went without any difficulty about his buſineſs, which he diſpatched ſooner and more ſucceſsfully, than he thought he ſhould have done. <hi>Nicholas de Laghi ex Andr. Ebor. Luſit. de Orat.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>7.</hi> Horſes loſe their lives for ſaving the honour due to the H. Hoſts.</head>
                  <p>THe Marſhal of <hi>Aumont,</hi> having brought the Town of St. <hi>Porcien</hi> in <hi>France</hi> under the League, his Souldiers pillaged the Pariſh Church, from whence they took away the Pix full of Hoſts, which they carried to the ſtable where their horſes ſtood. Where having emptied the Pix, they threw the Hoſts mingled with Oates into the Manger to feed their Horſes therewith; and as the horſes could not retire being tyed to the racks, to prevent the indignity that might happen, ſuddenly fire deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Heaven, and killed the horſes, without touching any ways the Headſtals. Thus the horſes loſt their Lives to hinder the affront and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65044:22"/> irreverence, which the Hereticks would have put upon the conſecrated Hoſts. <hi>P. Fodere Hiſt. de la province de S. Bonavent.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cheure,</hi> She-goat.</note>
                     <hi>8.</hi> A Shee-goat brings up an Infant devoted to the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>IN <hi>Poland</hi> an Infant was loſt, its parents being ignorant what became of it, for the ſpace of three years; the Father and Mother greatly afflicted at this miſhap, had recourſe to Heaven, to help them to ſome news of it. After all they made a vow, that if they could learn where it was, they would go a Pilgrimage to the H. Sacrament of <hi>Poſnanie.</hi> After this the Child was found in a Forreſt, and told them, that all that time, it had been fed by a Wild Shee-goat, which had alſo taken care to defend it againſt the Nights cold. <hi>Traterus apud Bzovium. Tom.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 205. <hi>in fine.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chiens,</hi> Dogs.</note>
                     <hi>9.</hi> Dogs revenge the injury done to the H. Hoſts.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>OPtatus Milevitan</hi> writes thus in his ſecond Book againſt <hi>Parmenion,</hi> that the Donatiſt-Hereticks, had given the H. Hoſt to Dogs, but that their own Dogs, inſtead of touching the H. Sacrament, to revenge the injury done to their Creator, fell upon their Maſters, and tore them in pieces.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>10.</hi> A Dog puniſhed by Heaven, for making a noiſe during the Maſſe.</head>
                  <p>IN the Life of Bl. <hi>Dalmace Monerio,</hi> of the Order of St. <hi>Dominick,</hi> it is reported, that this Father, in an Embaſſy of his to the Convent of <hi>Caſtellon,</hi> obſerved that a Lady called <hi>Villeneufue</hi> came to hear Maſſe at this Convents Church, accompanied with a little Dog, which made a great noiſe, with little Bells that hang round his neck. He intreated the Lady not to bring the Dog thither any more, which ſhe promiſed. One day having ſhut up her little Dog in a Chamber, ſhe came to Maſſe at the ſame Church: In her abſence, through the careleſneſs of a Servant that opened the Chamber door, the Dog ſlipping out, went ſtrait to Church to find again his Lady; as ſoon as he was entred, he fell a barking and making a great noiſe, to the diſturbing of the Prieſts Devotion who was ſaying Maſſe. Whereupon Bl. <hi>Dalmace</hi> lifting up his Eyes, prayed God not to ſuffer that Beaſt further to interrupt his Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Behold a ſtrange Prodigy! at that inſtant there appeared in the Church a great Dog with black and rugged Hair, ſeen by none either before or after, which ſeized ſo furiouſly on the Collar and Bells of this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65044:23"/> little Dog, that he lay overturned for dead on the ground, and the Bells he had round his neck, were never ſeen, the leaſt parcel of them any more. Of ſuch importance is ſilence for the right celebration of the H. Sacrifice; as S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> reports, that a certain H. Prieſt commanded the Frogs that croaked a little way from the Church, to hold their peace du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Divine Office, and they obeyed. <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Inſtit. Extract from the Life of</hi> B. Dalmace <hi>by</hi> Nic. Eymeric. Jac. Bleda. <hi>Mirac.</hi> 153. <hi>p.</hi> 296.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Dog reſpects and adores the H. Sacrament, and puniſhes the Blaſphemy of his Maſter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>NIcholas de Laghi,</hi> in his Book of the Miracles of the H. Sacrament ſays, that a Jew blaſpheming the H. Sacrament, dared to ſay in the preſence of many Chriſtians, that if they would give it to his Dog, that he would eat it up without ſhewing any regard to their God. The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians being very angry at this outragious ſpeech, and confiding in the Divine Providence; had a mind to bring it to tryal. Preſently one ſpreads a Napkin on the Table, upon which they laid many Hoſts, though there was onely one among them all that was conſecrated. The hungry Dog being put upon the ſame Table, ſet himſelf to eat them all up; but coming to that which had been conſecrated, without touching it, he kneeled down before it, and afterwards fell with rage upon his Maſter, catching him ſo cloſely by his Noſe, that he took it quite away with his Teeth. <hi>Jac. de Voragine in the Feaſt of Corpus Chriſti. De Laghi tract. d.</hi> 1. 9. <hi>c.</hi> 96. The ſame which S. <hi>Matthew</hi> warns ſuch like Blaſphemers, ſaying, <hi>Give not that which is holy to Dogs, leſt they turn again and rent you,</hi> c. 7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Peaſant being delivered from miſchievous Dogs, devoted himſelf to the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>A Peaſant of <hi>Poland,</hi> going one <hi>Sunday</hi> in the Forreſt, ſet himſelf to work, without regard to the holineſs of the day and to cut down a great Tree: While he was at work, there chanced to come thither a youth that was akin to him, with whom he took his repaſt, to recruit his ſtrength. Mean while he obſerved a Gum upon a Tree hard by, and ſet this Lad upon the Tree to gather it. The Tree about which the Peaſant had taken ſuch pains, and now bended towards the ground, came down at the ſame time and fell upon the Lad, &amp; kill'd him ſtark dead. The Man ſadly frighted with this accident, ran to the Village to get counſel and help; but in his way, behold, two black Dogs and very furious met him, and ran after him to fall upon him. He made the ſign of the Croſs for his defence, and vowed to undertake a Pilgrimage to the H. Sacrament
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65044:23"/> of <hi>Poſnanie,</hi> ſo he might but eſcape. As he thought them to be infernal Dogs, as indeed they were, ſo he perceived them ſuddenly to toſs up and down furiouſly, and to ſay to him with a Mans voice, If thou hadſt not defended thy ſelf with thoſe Arms, there had been an end of thy life, both body and ſoul. The Peaſant right glad to ſee himſelf out of danger, took care to bury the youth, and afterwards performed his vow, and repaired to <hi>Poſnanie,</hi> there to return thanks to God, and to adore the H. Sacrament. <hi>Treterus apud Bzovium. Tom.</hi> 5.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Infant was born with a Head like a Greyhound, whoſe Father was hunting without regarding to ſay Maſſe.</head>
                  <p>A Gentleman of the Low-Countrys uſed to go a hunting at all times, without any regard to the Maſſe or Divine Offices, for which he had been often blamed by his wife, who was a virtuous woman. Among many Children that ſhe bore him, ſhe had one born whoſe Head was like that of a Greyhound. The Mother and other women with her that beheld this, were all ſo confounded, that they thought it beſt to bury it privately, without making any noiſe. Upon this her husband returns home, and knowing his wife was brought a-bed, ask'd to ſee the Child. Upon the ſad ſilence they all kept, without making him any anſwer, he was enraged, and threatned, having drawn his Sword, to kill them all, if they would not ſhow it to him. His wife undertook to pacifie him, and telling him all that had paſt, afterwards taking up the Infant out of the ground, gave him a ſight of it, and then ſaid to him; Behold the fruit that is come of your not regarding the H. Sacrifice of the Maſſe, nor <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days</hi> more than other working-days. The husband was hereupon ſo much aſhamed, that he changed his courſe of life, and from that time forward, he had ſuch an eſteem of the Maſſe and Divine Offices, that it made him frequent it daily, to the great edification of his Family, and all under his charge. <hi>Joh. Herold. a. diſcip. Serm.</hi> 22. <hi>Nic. de Laghi, trac.</hi> 6. <hi>diſt.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 121. <hi>p.</hi> 259.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The admirable vigilancy and devoires of a Dog, in in honour of the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>THE Hiſtory of the Dog of <hi>Lisbon,</hi> is counted a prodigy: It is report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>F. Nieremberg</hi> almoſt in theſe words. In <hi>Lisbon,</hi> ſays, he, nigh to S. <hi>Juſtina</hi> dwelt a Confectioner, who kept a middleſiz'd Dog, whoſe Hair was marked with white Spots. It was two years ago (as he goes on) that he took up a Cuſtom to follow the Holy Sacrament, when it was carried to ſick perſons; they did not mind it till ſeveral months after, as neither ſeveral other circumſtances which begot admiration. Firſt, at
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65044:24"/> all times when they tolled the Church-Bell to give men notice of the honour which is to be paid to the Sacrament, on a ſudden this Dog went out of the houſe, after that he returned: When the ſign was given that the Prieſt was going abroad with the H. Sacrament, he haſtily returned to the Church, and ſtayed till he ſaw them come forth with the H. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt under a Canopy, then jumping towards the Children that march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before with the Cymbal, he went and came to this ſide and that ſide, as if he would ſet in order the proceſſion that was made for Jeſus Chriſt. The Dog is gentle and peaceable in his conditions, being accuſtomed to live among men, but yet at ſuch times, he neither obeys nor owns any perſon, no not his Maſter, if he ſhould chance to call him. In this manner he goes along to the ſick perſons houſe, waits at the door or in the ſtreet; afterwards brings back our Lord to the Church, and ſtays there till he be again placed in the Tabernacle. One night hearing the Bell for carrying out the Sacrament, he would go away, as his Cuſtom was, and finding the houſe-door ſhut, he came to his Maſters Chamber, and went round his bed, barking lovingly, that ſome body would open the door; which not being done, he found a Servant that was yet awake, after he had fawned on him, running round him, he pluckt him by the Coat, and drew him to the Gate, which when he had it open, he went ſtreight to Church, and the H. Sacrament being brought back, he return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed home. Another time accompanying the H. Sacrament, he met a Ped<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſleeping by a fountain, and taking his Aſſe by the Halter, he ran bark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at him, and never ceaſed till he had waked him, and ſaw him kneel and adore the H. Sacrament. Another time, following the H. Sacrament, he met a Country-woman upon an Aſſe, immediately he fell a barking a-loud, and leapt upon the woman, who being frighted, no body giving her notice, ſhe alighted and adored the H. Euchariſt, and the Dog with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making a noiſe purſued his way, leaving her in peace. Another time following the H. Sacrament, he met a Gentleman of Quality, who not ſeeming as if he would alight, he thereupon ſet upon him barking furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, till be had done ſo, and had adored Jeſus Chriſt. Nevertheleſs the horſe gave him a kick, which hurt the Dogs foot, which the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man commanded his Servant to take care of, but he would not be catch'd, but followed the H. Sacrament limping and holding one foot up; but when he came home, he let them of the houſe look after his hurt foot, and it was quickly healed. The ſame Father reports many other reſpects this Dog had ſhown, to conſtrain men to honour God in the H. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament; and though ſome endeavoured to withdraw him from ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, yet he continued them. The Dog was then alive at <hi>Lisbon,</hi> when the Reverend Father wrote his Hiſtory in the year 1635. <hi>P. Nieremberg in hiſtoria Naturae.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:65044:24"/>
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Colombes,</hi> Pigeons.</note>Several Holy Prieſts have been honoured by Pigeons, while they ſaid Maſſe.</head>
                  <p>SEveral have ſeen Pigeons often perch upon the heads of ſuch as have celebrated the H. Sacrifice of the Maſſe. It happened ſo to St. <hi>Kentigerne</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to St. <hi>Cunibert,</hi> to B. <hi>Anſelme</hi> of the <hi>Ciſtercian</hi> Order, to B. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher</hi> companion of St. <hi>Francis.</hi> So it alſo happened to Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> IX. when he ſaid Maſſe in the deſert of <hi>Camaldoli,</hi> which was a preſage, that he would come to be Pope. The ſame happened to Pope <hi>Marcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> II. while he ſaid Maſſe in the Church of our Lady of <hi>Loretta,</hi> a mark of the Soveraign dignity to which he was called by Heaven, and was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards confirmed to him by the Mother of God, whilſt he ſaid Maſſe at the ſame Altar. <hi>Turſellin. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 20. <hi>hiſtoriae Lauretanae.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Pigeon brings a H. Hoſt, to communicate one newly Converted to the Faith.</head>
                  <p>THe H. Martyrs <hi>Fauſtinus</hi> and <hi>Jovita,</hi> having baptized at <hi>Milan</hi> a Souldier named <hi>Secundus,</hi> as they were about to give him the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, according to the uſage of the Church, having no bread at all wherewith to conſecrate, a Pigeon flew into the Priſon with an Hoſt in her Bill, and having aſſured them it had been conſecrated, being ſent thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Heaven, they therewith communicated the new-made Chriſtian. <hi>Surius in vita. SS. M. M. Fauſtini &amp; Jovitae.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pigeons informed the Eaſtern Biſhops concerning the Holineſs of the Sacrifice, and of the Pope that celebrated.</head>
                  <p>ABout the year 1145, in the days of Pope <hi>Lucius,</hi> or as others of Pope <hi>Eugenius,</hi> Embaſſadors above a 1000. in number from the <hi>Armeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Biſhops, and from their Metropolitan whom they call Catholick, that is to ſay Univerſal, came to find the Pope at <hi>Rome,</hi> to ſubmit themſelves to his Obedience, and to take from him the moſt perfect form, which he ſhould judge they ought to obſerve in the moſt holy Sacrifice of the Maſſe. The Pope received them very courteouſly, and invited them to come to ſee him officiate on a ſolemn day that drew neer. The Legats who were alſo Biſhops, and had made a journey of 18 months, failed not to open all the Eyes of their ſouls and bodies, to obſerve this Pontifical Maſſe. After the conſecration, they ſaw a great light, like a globe of the Suns Rays to fall down upon the Head of the Pope, and to encompaſs it like a Crown, and two Pigeons alſo flying up and deſcending, without being able to diſcover any hole in the Church, through which that light and thoſe Pigeons might come in; And when the Communion was over,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65044:25"/> all diſappeared: Thus our Lord would honour his Vicar in the preſence of theſe <hi>Armenian</hi> Legats, that ſo, being raviſh'd with the Sanctity of his Vicar, and the wonders of ſo holy a Sacrifice, they might ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves more eaſily to the Succeſſors of St. <hi>Peter. Corbin. mirac.</hi> 740. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neg.</hi> 174. <hi>p.</hi> 460.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Pigeon ſucks the Blood conſecrated by a wicked Prieſt, and reſtores it to the Prieſt, after he had confeſſed his Sin.</head>
                  <p>IN the year 1200. at <hi>Leon</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> a Prieſt, tho' he had defiled himſelf with a woman, yet dared to approach to the Altar, on the holy night of the Nativity of our Lord, without confeſſing himſelf beforehand. At the firſt and ſecond Maſſe, before he had conſecrated, and ſaid the <hi>Pater-noſter,</hi> on a ſudden a Pigeon flew with great ſwiftneſs towards the Prieſt, and putting its Bill into the Chalice, ſuck'd out all the Blood, and with her wings took up the Hoſts out of the Prieſts hands and flew away. The Prieſt being frighted and concerned in this accident that was repeated, took care not to paſſe to a third Maſſe, without confeſſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and repenting of his Sin. In the ſequel, as he was celebrating the third time, and came to the <hi>Pater,</hi> the Pigeon returned, and putting her Bill into the Chalice, caſt up again all the Wine ſhe had ſucked, and let fall the two Hoſts ſhe had carried away, at the foot of the Chalice. This ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary wonder, teaches Prieſts a good Leſſon, how they ought to be diſpoſed, when they are to celebrate, and approach the Altar. <hi>Fr.</hi> James Bleda, <hi>in his Treatiſe of the Fraternity of the H. Sacrament, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle</hi> 222. <hi>who ſays that he had taken it out of the Spaniſh Chronicles of</hi> Peter Michael Carbonel.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>S. <hi>Edmund</hi> was communicated by a Pigeon.</head>
                  <p>ST. <hi>Edmund</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> after he had applied his mind ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly to conſider the Argument of the H. Trinity, on purpoſe to prepare himſelf for a publick Diſpute, which was to be held upon this Myſtery, retiring himſelf late to take his reſt, he thought that in the night time a Pigeon brought to him the H. Sacrament, and that he received it. On the day of diſputation, he came into the Aſſembly, and diſcourſed in ſo high a manner upon this Subject, that all that were preſent were greatly aſtoniſhed and edified. Bleda 1. <hi>Mirac.</hi> 127. <hi>p.</hi> 227. <hi>ex ſum.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Pigeon marks out the outſide lines, and form of a Chappel of our Ladies.</head>
                  <p>A Gentlewoman of <hi>Bononia</hi> called <hi>Ricoiola Galoni,</hi> with her Husband, had made a vow to build a Chappel to the Virgin upon a Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain nigh to that Town; they had only digg'd for the foundations, when the Maſons perceived a Pigeon, that turned round about them, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:65044:25"/> ſeemed to mark a certain ſpace with little ſticks which ſhe had gathered together hither and thither, and this by the ſpace of two days. The No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty of the thing made them look upon it as extraordinary; ſo that the report of it having run abroad, many came thither from <hi>Bononia.</hi> The Biſhop came over thither with his Clergy, and had the pleaſure to ſee with his own Eyes this Pigeon, how buſie ſhe was in making this round, without being concerned at the great number of perſons that obſerved her. He preſently judged that the H. Virgin had ſent it to trace the boundaries of the Chappel which <hi>Ricciola</hi> had projected. Wherefore he adviſed her to cauſe it to be built round in the ſame place that the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon had marked; which ſhe did with ſuch diligence, that on the firſt day of <hi>September</hi> following, it was ready for Conſecration: The frequent Miracles that were done, ſufficiently teſtified, that the H. Virgin had choſe that place for to be honoured there. <hi>Sigonius in Epiſcopis Bononi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſibus; Leander in deſcript. Italiae.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Ravens, Crows, Choughs, and other Birds of prey,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Corbeux,</hi> Ravens. <hi>Corneilles,</hi> Crows. <hi>Choüettes,</hi> Choughs.</note> aſſembled ordinarily nigh to <hi>Ravenna,</hi> on <hi>S. Apollinarius</hi>'s day, during the Divine Office, that was ſaid there.</head>
                  <p>A Great number of Ravens, Crows, Choughs, &amp; other ſuch like birds, flockt together yearly from all parts of <hi>Italy</hi> near the Town of <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venna,</hi> at the Feaſt of S. <hi>Apollinarius,</hi> firſt Biſhop of this Town, for to make an extraordinary concourſe to this ſolemnity, during the time of celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Office in the preſence of the H. Sacrament. The people of <hi>Raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> for an acknowledgment of the reſpect they ſhewed to their Apoſtle, had in readineſs the dead body of a Horſe, upon which theſe Birds made their repaſt, before their return to the place from whence they came. Some attribute this marvel to a miracle that had been wrought by the H. Biſhop; and it might happen that this ſort of Birds, might have been baniſh'd and driven away, becauſe they defiled the Church with their dung, and hindred the Divine Office at Maſſe and other times by their doleful and troubleſome noiſe, and for this reaſon ſome believe that the City took its name from theſe Birds. <hi>Niremberg. de mirac. naturae, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 389.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="D" type="part">
               <head>D.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Dragon is made tame by the vertue of the H. Maſſe.</head>
                  <p>ST. <hi>Paul</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Leon,</hi> of the Country of <hi>Ireland,</hi> being intreated by the Inhabitants of a Sea-Town, to deliver them from a Dragon that ruined their Country, and hindred them from going freely abroad
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65044:26"/> the fields, he aſſured them of the Divine help, upon condition that they repented, and renounced their Superſtitions. Which when they had done, he appointed his Nephew to prepare an Altar at which he might ſay Maſſe. When Maſſe was done, he went out of the Church, and being filled with divine confidence, he with a loud voice ſummoned this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage beaſt to make his appearance, without doing hurt to any one. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately the Dragon appeared with open mouth and rolling Eyes ſparkling with choler, and went ſtreight towards the Saint, caſting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at his feet. St. <hi>Paul,</hi> caſt a ſtole round his neck, and fixing his ſtaff in the ground, he there bound the Dragon without any reſiſtance, or mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any motion to get away from him, as if he had been tamed and made as gentle as a Lamb. <hi>Colganus in vita S.</hi> Jaonez. 2. <hi>Martii, pag.</hi> 442. <hi>n.</hi> 8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Dragons revenge the injuries done to the H. Euchariſt.</head>
                  <p>CErtain Inhabitants of a Town in <hi>Italy</hi> having received the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion on an <hi>Eaſter-day,</hi> through great irreverence ſpent the reſt of the day in ſports and laſcivious dancings. The Divine vengeance followed them quickly after. For among their puniſhments God ſent a Deluge of Water upon their Land, which overwhelmed all their Harveſt of Corn, and drowned all their Meadows; from whence came forth Dragons that encumbred their ways when they were dryed, ſo that none could walk into the Field without fear of his Life. The Country lying wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate, a Holy perſon, moved with compaſſion, prayed to God earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to turn away his wrath, or at leaſt to tell him the cauſe of it. Upon this an Angel appeared to him, and asked him this Queſtion, If any perſon ſhould be ſo daring, as to lay hands upon the Emperours Son, and by wicked Treachery and Treaſon caſt him into a dark and ſtinking Dungeon, what puniſhment would this inſolent perſon deſerve? The good man anſwered, That he deſerved to be put to death and quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: But, added the Angel, What if another ſhould take the Pix, in which the H. Hoſt is kept, and before a great number of people, ſhould caſt it into a ſink full of filth and naſtineſs, what puniſhment was due to this ſacrilegious perſon? The H. man reply'd, That he ought to be burnt as Hereticks are. Upon this the Angel ſaid; The Inhabitants of this place have put the Son of God into a ſtinking obſcure Priſon; and, which is more, they have caſt the H. Pix, that is, their heart, into a dunghill of all ſorts of uncleanneſs and vanities, for which crimes they have merited theſe and greater Chaſtiſements. When the people un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood this, they ſet themſelves to repent of their ſins, that they might be delivered from theſe puniſhments. <hi>In Spec. Exempl. tit. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char. Ex.</hi> 13.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="E" type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:65044:26"/>
               <head>E.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Elephants at <hi>Goa,</hi> come in the Proceſſion of the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>I Find the Elephants alſo do honour to their Creator in the H. Euchariſt As this is a Creature braving and deſirous of glory, they are wont at <hi>Goa,</hi> a capital City of the Eaſt Indies, to introduce them in a ſolemn Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion they make in honour of the H. Sacrament, on <hi>Corpus Chriſti</hi> day. The young ones march firſt, after follow the older Elephants all magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently cloathed, carrying the Croſſe and Armes of <hi>Portugal,</hi> painted in their natural colours on the head, and their whole Body; each of them carries Men on his Back, one five or ſix Trumpeters, others as many Muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, whoſe loud Eccho's are heard during the Proceſſion. This vaſt Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal, which is eaſily chafed at other times, at this time marches with a gate ſo peaceable, but accompanied with ſuch gravity, that he ſeems to appland himſelf and ſwell as men are wont to do, in this Pomp and Magnificence: All Men and all Animals render this homage to their Creator. <hi>Quantum potes, tantum aude. Nieremberg. in Hiſt. naturae, l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 88.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Ermine <hi>ſerves for a ſubject,</hi> to honour the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>NIgh to <hi>Mariemburg</hi> in <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> a Carpenter being in company with a quarelſome perſon in the ſame Lodging, and being forced to defend himſelf, he grievouſly wounded this impertinent fellow. For this he was caſt in Priſon, and afterwards having learnt the wounded man was like to dye, he ſought all ways to get his Liberty. And calling to mind the Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles which the H. Sacrament of <hi>Poſnanie</hi> wrought in high <hi>Poland,</hi> he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to take a Journey thither, if Heaven would bring him out of the danger wherein he now was. Preſently after he had made this Vow, he ſaw an Ermine creep along the wall of the Tower, to a certain place; which he look'd upon as a good token of his Deliverance. He went to that place without delay, and found Tools there, fit to open a breach for him to eſcape Priſon. In concluſion, going to work with them, the Stones were looſened and tumbled down without much difficulty, Heaven ſeeming to cooperate with his juſt deſire. When the paſſage was opened thrô which 2 men might go, he haſtily ſprang out of Priſon. Afterward he went out of the Town, without being diſcovered, althô the Magiſtrates had ſent a Meſſenger after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to apprehend him: So he arrived ſafely at <hi>Poſnanie,</hi> where he declared this Miracle, and performed the Vow he had made to go thither, to render his thanks to God. <hi>Traterus</hi> apud <hi>Bzovium.</hi> tom. 15,</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="F" type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:65044:27"/>
               <head>F.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Falcon teaches us the reverence and decency due to places, where the H. Sacrament lies, and is kept.</head>
                  <p>IT is reported of a Falcon, which in the days of S. <hi>Brigit</hi> the Virgin, made its abode continually in a Towre of a Church, that for the reverence owing to the place where the H. Sacrament is kept, he would not ſuffer the company of any female there, but at breeding time it retired afar off from thence to the Mountains, and having ſatisfied nature returned again to its ancient abode; leaving a good example of the decency that is owing to Churches and Holy places. <hi>Nieremb. in hiſt. Nat. l.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 38.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">Fourmis. <hi>Ants.</hi>
                     </note>Ants by the Puniſhment that befell them, ſhew the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence due to Altars, and to the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>IN a Church of one of our Colledges in <hi>Portugal,</hi> on the day of a great Feaſt, the Sexton had ſet Pots with fine Poſies of Flowers, round the Tabernacle where the H. Sacrament repoſes: In the night a troop of Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires, which had their retreat not far from the Altar, drawn by the ſweet ſmell of theſe flowers, came neer to the Tabernacle, to forrage for Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: but this their irreverence was immediately chaſtized, for the day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the Sexton lifting up the Tapeſtry that covered the Altar, he found them all dead neer the Tabernacle. <hi>Ex Literis ann: prov. Luſitaniae.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="G" type="part">
               <head>
                  <note place="margin">Gelines. <hi>Henns.</hi>
                  </note>G.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Henns honour the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>BL. <hi>Ida</hi> of <hi>Lovain,</hi> before ſhe entred into the <hi>Ciſtertian</hi> Order, had uſed to feed Henns and other tame Foules; and after ſhe was a profeſſed Nun, ſhe had ſo great devotion to the H. Sacrifice of the Maſſe, that ſhe brought thither all her Henns and other Poultry, which followed her at her call, and in the Church, as far as they were able, humbled themſelves, and kept themſelves before the moſt Holy Sacrament of the Altar without making any noiſe, to the admiration of all the people there preſent. Corbin <hi>in his Panegyrick on the H. Sacrament, Miracle</hi> 741. p. 504.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Hen revenges the injury done to the H. Euchariſt.</head>
                  <p>IN the year 1561. at <hi>Nimegen,</hi> a Town of <hi>Gelderland,</hi> two Libertine Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, ſtopping at an Alehouſe the ſecond day of the Feaſt of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> made a challenge, which could ſooneſt ſwallow his Egge. One of them hearing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:65044:27"/> the Bell which uſes to be carried when the Prieſt goes with the H. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to a ſick Perſon, ſaid, that he would ſooner ſwallow his Egge, than the ſick Perſon his God or Idol, for ſo he called the H. Sacrament in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; but this he did to his own hurt: for the Egg ſtopt in his throat, and he being ſeized with fear, took a Tallow-candle, to make it paſs down to the bottom of his Stomach, but all in vain: for the Tallow ſtopt in the paſſage, without his being able to bring up any thing ſave onely the wicke, and in this eſtate, he fell down dead, with a face as black as an Ethiopian, and his throat ſpoyled by a divine Puniſhment. Alſo the Egg that had ſtopt, having made a bunch between the fleſh and the skin, appeared not in the throat, but on the other ſide of his neck. This Miracle happened on the 8th of <hi>April</hi> in the year above mention'd. <hi>Bredembachius. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 60. <hi>Sacr. Collat.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Grenoville.</hi> A Frog.</note>Frogs give reſpect to the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> Ferrier</hi> remarks in the Life of S. <hi>Lindanus</hi> the Abbot, that the ſaid Saint hearing one day a number of Frogs croaking with troubleſome noiſe in a Marſh nigh to the Church, and diſturbing the Prieſt, and thoſe that were preſent at Maſſe; he went and ſmote thoſe waters with his Staff; upon which, all the Froggs were ſtill, and after that time were never heard to croak more. <hi>In the Catalogue of the Saints of Italy on the</hi> 3. <hi>of July.</hi> p. 204.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="H" type="part">
               <head>H.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hirondelle,</hi> A Swallow.</note>
                     <hi>Swallows.</hi> The Honour paid by this ſort of Birds.</head>
                  <p>THe Bl. Father <hi>Francis ò Fabiano,</hi> of the Order of S. <hi>Francis,</hi> who was a very devout Perſon, Praying one day before the H. Sacrament, and conſidering the great Love Chriſt Jeſus bore towards us in his Death and Paſſion, and on the other ſide, turning his Eyes upon mens ingratitude, who think ſo little of it, as if theſe benefits did not concern them; the Swallows that had made their neſts round about the Church, began to chatter ſo troubleſomely, that they interrupted the quiet, which Meditation and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation do's require; and they continuing their chirping noiſe, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to withdraw, and to return no more to that place: they obeyed readily this his command; and it was obſerv'd that all that year, not one Swallow appeared any more in that place. <hi>Wading. l.</hi> 3. <hi>ad. an.</hi> 1322.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another Hiſtory of the ſame kind.</head>
                  <p>FAther <hi>Peter Regalatus,</hi> of the ſame Order, a Prieſt of Eminent vertue, and a Superiour of the Houſe of <hi>Aquila</hi> in <hi>Spain.</hi> He being a Perſon given much to Prayer, his example drew many other Religious Perſons to imitate
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:65044:28"/> him, ſo that, if they were not otherwiſe hindred, one might find them in the Church before the H. Sacrament, praying. But as Prayer requires great quiet and recollection to find there and taſt the Spirit of God, they found themſelves deprived thereof by the troubleſome noyſe of Swallows, that had their neſts round the Church, and made their complaint of it to their Superior. The Holy man willing to give ſome Satisfaction to the devout Priers, lifting up his hand and raiſing his voice, he commanded theſe Birds to be gone from the Church, and not to return thither any more, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered them to ſignifye the ſame command to the reſt of their company. Oh admirable event! after this time not one Swallow dared to make a neſt about the Church, without receiving a ſure payment for its diſobedience. In the Memoires prepared for his Canonization, it is reported, that one or two Swallows flying about in the Church, fell down dead upon the Pavement. <hi>Wading. Tom.</hi> 5. <hi>ad an.</hi> 1448. <hi>n.</hi> 9.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="J" type="part">
               <head>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jument.</hi> A Mare.</note>J.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Jumens.</hi> Mares adore the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>IN the year 1317, and the 25th of <hi>July,</hi> in a place called <hi>Vivieres,</hi> nigh to the Town of <hi>Fumay,</hi> in the County of <hi>Looz;</hi> the Vicar of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named place, was required to carry the Sacrament to a Sick perſon. He went thither, and being arrived at the Houſe, he layd down the Box (or Pix) in which the Hoſt was, upon a Table, to go and hear the Confeſſion of the Dying Perſon. Mean while ſome of the houſe, not duly conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, came round the Pix, opened it, and there touched the Hoſt with very great irreverence, and after ſhut it up again. The Prieſt after he had diſpoſed his Penitent, took up the Pix, and came back to him to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate him. Upon the opening of it, he perceived that the Hoſt had iſſued out blood, and was ſtained with it, and ſtuck to the Linnen that was within. This ſight caſt him into a great fright, ſo that he durſt not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate his Sick man, but having comforted him, and reſpited the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion to another time, he carried back the Pix and the Hoſt to the Church. The Pariſh Prieſt knowing what had paſſed, commanded his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car to carry the Hoſt to the Monaſtery of <hi>Herkenorode</hi> to conſult with a venerable and knowing Prieſt, who lived there: he did ſo; but as he was upon the rode to accompliſh it, the Mares, Aſſes and other Beaſts that paſſed in the Fields where he went, paid their acknowledgments to their Creator, adoring him with bended knees; and the Vicar arriving at the Church of the Monaſtery, two Bells in the Steeple, rang of their own accord, the Beaſts and other animate things, bearing more reſpect to the H. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:65044:28"/> than Men had done. At his arrival they Sung the Maſs of the 1ſt. of Auguſt, <hi>(S. Petri ad vincula)</hi> the Prieſt that celebrated knowing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of what had paſt, yet went back a little from the Altar, to adore the H. Sacrament with a low bowing of his head. Whilſt he did thus, our Lord appeared to him in a humane form, with a certain Crown upon his head: which was not ſeen by any but himſelf: at the ſame time one poſſeſſed was delivered from the evil Spirit, and ſince that time the H. Sacrament has not ceaſed, nor now ceaſes to produce ſome miraculous Effects. <hi>Bened. Conan. in hiſtor. Euchar. l. d. c.</hi> 82. <hi>ex Chryſoſt. Henriquez in Menol. Ciſterc. ad</hi> 29 <hi>Julii.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Mares and Oxen paſſing through a Marſh, adore our Lord in the H. Euchariſt.</head>
                  <p>IN the year 1399, a Woman and her Daughter that ſerved a Jew at <hi>Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanie</hi> in higher <hi>Poland,</hi> engaged themſelves for a great Summ of Money, to deliver conſecrated Hoſts to the Jews. To effect this, on the day of the Virgins Aſſumption, they lay hid in the Church of the F. F. <hi>Dominicans,</hi> and when the Friers were gone to Dinner, the Daughter being upon the watch, the Mother went towards the Tabernacle, and thô the firſt and ſecond time of her approach ſhe fell backwards, being repuls'd by a divine force, yet ſhe came on the third time and opened it: ſhe took out of the Pix three Hoſts which they delivered to the miſerable Jews, after they of this Sect had aſſembled together in a Cellar under-ground, they threw them down contemptuouſly upon a Table, and after they had uttered many Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, they ſtabb'd them with a Dagger, from whence iſſued out great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Blood, and the firſt mans face was ſo covered therewith, that he could never wipe it away, but by the flames of his Puniſhment; the Cellar alſo was all full of Blood, which they could not neither any ways get off. The Jews being frighted with theſe wonders, charged two among them, to hide theſe Hoſts in the Mariſhes out of the Town: During this journey many Miracles happened.</p>
                  <p>On Sunday the Octave of the Aſſumption, a Neat-herd and his Son; led the Mares and Oxen they had the charge of, to theſe Mariſhes; the Father left his Son there, whilſt he went to be preſent at the Divine offices. This youth named <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaw theſe three Hoſts lifted up in the Air, and fly like Butterflies, which the Mares that paſſed there, adored kneeling; and the Father at his return ſaw the ſame, his Oxen kneeling alſo down to adore their Creator.</p>
                  <p>The Neat-herd returning to the Town, reported to the Magiſtrate that which he had ſeen, but inſtead of being believed; he was thrown in Priſon for a Fool; where he crying to Heaven for ſuccour, the Priſon gates opened
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65044:29"/> of themſelves, and he went out, and preſented himſelf again before the Magiſtrate, who having obſerved, that he was no man of tricks, made their report of it to the Biſhop, who went thither with great Pomp and Proceſſion; the Hoſts were gathered up by a Prieſt at the Biſhops command, and ſearch being made the hardened Jews were burnt, and their Goods confiſcated. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ladiſlaus</hi> King of <hi>Poland</hi> cauſed a Church to be built in that place, under the Title of <hi>the Body of Jeſus Christ,</hi> where God wrought Miracles of all ſorts: among which they reckoned 36 raiſed from the dead, and from the beginning of theſe Miracles, to the year 1604, their number arrived to 382. This Hiſtory was written by <hi>Tho. Treterus,</hi> Almoner to <hi>Cardinal Roſius,</hi> and afterward Canon and Sacriſt of <hi>Varme</hi> in <hi>Poland. Bzovius reports this hiſtory in his</hi> 5th <hi>Tome</hi> in the year above noted.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Woman appeared in form of a Mare, for her negligence in frequenting the Communion.</head>
                  <p>A Magician not being able by his Charms to corrupt the Chaſtity of a Woman, in favour of a young Man, who hired him thereto, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched her, in ſuch ſort, that ſhe was ſeen by her Husband and by all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the ſhape of a Mare: She was brought to S. <hi>Macarius</hi> who took a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Charm with Holy-Water, and told her, that this misfortune had happened to her, for having omitted to frequent the Communion, which ſhe had abſtained from for ſeveral Weeks. <hi>Palladius in S. Maca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ius life,</hi> where that excellent Sentence of the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> is brought, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <q>We excite and exhort the faithful to their Combat, and that they may not be left naked, we put on and arm them with the protection of the Body and Blood of the Lord: And ſince the Euchariſt is moſt profitable for the defence of thoſe that receive it, we deſiring their Security againſt the Adverſary, let us arm them with the defence of our Lords whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Viande, which the Council calls <hi>Munimentum dominicae ſalubritatis.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="L" type="part">
               <head>
                  <note place="margin">Lapins <hi>Conies.</hi>
                  </note>L.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Conies adore the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>IN the year 1412. one <hi>John Vanlangarſterden</hi> came to lodge at <hi>Herental</hi> in <hi>Brabant,</hi> and went out every day ſecretly to catch a Prize: one day en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring in company into the Church of <hi>Vectreleſande,</hi> he carried away from thence the Chalice with the Pix, wherein there were five conſecrated Hoſts. As he was thinking to return to <hi>Herental</hi> with his booty, and was upon the Rode thither, he was much ſurprized, finding that he could not advance forward, do what he could, and at the ſame time knew not whether he
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:65044:29"/> went. This wandring, made him inwardly reflect and think that this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to him for his ſin. Hereupon he reſolved to throw the ſtollen Hoſts into the River, and going to put this in execution, he found himſelf ſtopt ſhort, without being able to ſtir from the place, where he was. He being then hard by a Coney-Warren, that he might rid himſelf of thoſe Hoſts, he threw and hid them in a Coney-burrough. After which he found himſelf at liberty to return to his Lodging; where the Provoſt of <hi>Herental,</hi> upon the noiſe that ran up and down of the Robbery, cauſed him to be arreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and putting him to the rack, it was not long ere he confeſſed the ſteal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Chalice and the Pix, without ſaying any thing of the Hoſts. But when the Sentence was paſs'd on him to dye, his Confeſſor preſſed him to tell what was become of the Hoſts, and yet he would not ſay a word about it, till he was juſt going to be thrown off the Ladder; then he freely confeſſed the whole Fact, and diſcover'd the place where he had put the Hoſts. Upon which he was brought down the Ladder, and led to the Warren, a number of People accompanying him, and he ſhowed the hole where he had caſt them. But not finding them there, one caſting his Eyes about, ſaw them laid orderly upon the Graſs, and round about the Conies kneeling, adored with all reſpect their Creator. It was eight days ſince this was done, and yet among all the Snows and Raines and other Injuries of the Air which happen in the Month of <hi>February,</hi> they found the Hoſt entire and not at all endammaged: the very Elements and Beaſts owning their Creator, whilſt the Hereticks deny and blaſpheme him. The Criminal was brought back to the Place of Execution, and was burnt, for expiation of his enormous Crime. Upon the noiſe of this great Miracle, <hi>Antony</hi> Duke of <hi>Brabant</hi> with the Princeſs <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his Wife, came to the Place with a world of followers, to teſtify their Piety towards the H. Sacrament. A Chappel was built over the Coney-borrough, where the Hoſts had been thrown, which is to be ſeen to this day under the Altar. Great Devotion continued always, and does to this day towards this place, but the Hoſts have been loſt by the fury of our new <hi>Iconolaſts</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts. Auguſt: Wickman in Brab. Mariana. P. Rivero in append. ad ſolenne ſapientiae convivium.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Linx ou chere ſavage.</hi> A Shamois or wild Goat.</note>A Shamois, or wild Goat, ſerves to honour the H. Sacrament, in the deliverance of the Emperor <hi>Maximilian</hi> I.</head>
                  <p>ABout the year 1470. the Emperor <hi>Maximilian</hi> hunting this ſort of Game, one day upon the Mountains by the City of <hi>Inspruch,</hi> as he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued one of them, being carried on with an earneſt deſire to ſeize it, he ran ſo high upon the point of one of thoſe Mountains before he was aware, that he ſaw himſelf in a condition never to get off, without apparent danger
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:65044:30"/> of falling into an horrid precipice, which he had before his Eyes, ſo that ſeeing himſelf loſt, after he had continued there two whole days, he called to his followers, who all in tears viewed him below, not being able to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour him, that they ſhould go and intreat the neighbouring Pariſh Prieſt to bring the H. Sacrament of the Altar, that before he dyed he might have at leaſt the ſatisfaction to ſee it and adore it, ſince he could not receive it, in the extremity to which he was reduced. They preſently did ſo, and he having devoutly adored the H. Euchariſt, he ſaw immediately a young Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd by him, who removing the flint Stones with his Crooke, to plain as it were the way for him, ſaid to him have a good heart Prince, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me; He being thus incouraged, began to deſcend the Hill with him, and preſently was brought to his followers, who while they were conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering this Shepherd, and ſpeaking of the great reward he deſerved for his good Service, he was vaniſhed and they ſaw him no more. Upon this they believed him to be an Angel, and with great joy conducted their young Maſter to the Palace of the Emperor <hi>Frederick</hi> 4th his Father, who immediately went to return publick thanks to God for ſo miraculous a Deliverance. <hi>S. Romuald in theſaur. chron. ad. an. cit. ex Pighio in ſuo Hercule prod.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Loup.</hi> A Wolf.</note>A Wolf, in conſideration of the Communion received, quits his Prey, ſo doing homage to the H. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</head>
                  <p>A Devout Convert of a Monaſtery of the <hi>Ciſtertians,</hi> who had the charge of the Muttons and Sheep, having one day devoutly received the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, went thence to his Flock, to look whether any diſorder had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened there. Who then ſaw a Wolf returning to the Wood loaded with one of his Sheep: the good Frier fell upon his knees, and looking up to Heaven made this Prayer. O Jeſus the good Shepherd, the Lamb of God, that takeſt away the ſins of the World, whom I tho' unworthy have this day received, I recommend this Sheep to thee, do thou look to it which has been put under my keeping; for my part, I ſee it ſafe in your hand, but I can no ways ſave it. Behold a ſtrange thing! upon this prayer, this ravenous Beaſt immediately leaves his Prey, without hurting or touching it. The devout Frier, after he had rendred his thankſgiving, brought back the Sheep to the Flock, with great Joy. <hi>P. Major. in Spec. ex hiſt. Euchar. ex</hi> 20.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:65044:30"/>
                  <head>A Man and his Wife being transformed into a Wolf by force of an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precation, deſire to receive the communion, which was done to the Woman, being at the point of death.</head>
                  <p>A Prieſt of <hi>Ireland</hi> travelling from the Province of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> towards <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> was forced to paſs a whole Night in a Forreſt. As his Boy that went with him had lighted a fire under a thick Tree, they perceived a Wolf to draw towards them, and being come up to them, ſpake to them thus; Be well aſſured and fear nothing, ſince there is no cauſe for it. They however could not help being afraid at the ſight of a Wolf, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him ſpeak like a man, whereupon the Prieſt conjured him in the name of the H. Trinity not to do them harm, and to do declare what he was, and of what country, appearing in the likeneſs of a Wolf: Thereupon he ſaid to him, that he was of a certain race of Men called <hi>Oſſirians</hi> (Oſſiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſes) from whence every ſeven years, by force of an imprecation made by S. <hi>Noel</hi> the Abbot, two from among them, a Male and a Female, were conſtrained to leave their Country, and loſing the outward ſhape of a Man, to live under the hide and ſhape of a Wolf. After which term of years, if they ſurvived, two others were brought into the ſame condition, and they returned back to their Country, and reſumed their firſt form. I have not far from this place, added he, a ſhe Mate that lies very ſick, whom I intreat you in Charity to go ſee her and comfort her. The Prieſt following the Wolf ſome time, perceived at length a She-Wolf in the thicket of a great Tree complaining like a Woman. As ſoon as ſhe ſaw the Prieſt ſhe ſalut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, and courteouſly gave him thanks for his viſit, praiſing God for having obtained this comfort, in the extream danger, wherein ſhe found her ſelf: after this ſhe pray'd him to do her the kindneſs, that ſhe might receive the Communion at his hands, that ſo ſhe might die more conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly. The Prieſt having told her, that he had never an Hoſt about him to do it withal, the Wolf that was gone a little aſide, returned and ſhow'd him a little book, wherein he had ſome conſecrated Hoſts; and then was importunate with him, that he would not diſappoint his wife of this laſt and important Conſolation; and to take away from him all doubt, making uſe of his foot inſtead of a hand, he thruſt back the Skin that covered her, from the head to the Navel, and then he ſaw her in the ſhape of an old Woman. At length, tho' with ſome apprehenſion, the Prieſt communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated the ſick ſhe-Wolf, which preſſed him to it with all poſſible earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. All being over, the Wolf brought the Prieſt back to his fire, ſtay'd with him all night, and in the morning brought him out of the Forreſt, and ſhow'd him a ſhorter and ſafer way for him to take, to arrive at the place, whither he was to go. <hi>Nieremberg. de naturis Mirac. in Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rop. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 42.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:65044:31"/>
                  <head>A Wolf abuſing the Beaſts of S. <hi>Iſidore,</hi> thereupon dyed, by virtue of the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>S. <hi>Iſidore</hi> Patron of the City of <hi>Madrid,</hi> and by his Calling a Labourer, praying before the H. Sacrament, and hearing Maſs in S. <hi>Magdalen</hi>'s Church, ſome Boys came to tell him, that a Wolf was abuſing one of his Beaſts; to whom he replyed, My Children go in peace, and went on with his Prayer in the ſame place. When Prayer was done, he went to the place which thoſe Children gave him notice of, and there he found the Wolf lying dead before his Beaſt, that remained alive. Upon this won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful accident, he returned to the Church, to render his thanks to God for it. <hi>Bleda. mirac.</hi> 245. <hi>p.</hi> 153.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="M" type="part">
               <head>M.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mouche.</hi> A Fly.</note>A Fly ſatisfies for the irreverence ſhe had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted toward the H. Sacrament by being burnt.</head>
                  <p>S. <hi>Annon</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Colen,</hi> a Prelat of admirable devotion, celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the H. Sacrifice of the Maſse; as he had broken the Hoſt, and let fall one piece of it into the Chalice, holding the other piece in his hand, he fell upon conſidering its greatneſs, compared with his own unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and baſeneſs. Mean while, by the artifice of the Devil, a Fly ſpotted with various colours came flying about, and with one wheeling of her Wing and a ſtroke of her Teeth, carried away a piece of the Hoſt: The S. when he perceived it, reſented it with great ſorrow, and abundance of tears more than ordinary, fearing that this miſhap came by his own fault, through the long pauſe he made while he was in meditation and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation; and his apprehenſion of it was ſo great, that he turned pale like a dead Perſon. But God who knew the heart of the Saint, did not ſuffer him to lye long in this affliction; for he conſtrained this Fly to bring back the ſame parcel of the Hoſt, and put it under the Patine; and when it at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to fly away, was there ſtopt inmovably, as deſerving to be burnt. In fine, S. <hi>Annon</hi> made it be taken up and burnt, for the indignity it had committed. And thus it is that God proves and comforts his Servants.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Surius ad</hi> 4. <hi>Decemb. Novarini. in agno Euchariſt. n.</hi> 802.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another ſuch like Story.</head>
                  <p>A Certain Prieſt celebrating the Euchariſt in the preſence of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, as he was come to the fraction of the Bread, a Fly came flying with great eagerneſs round the Chalice, as if ſhe would force her entrance into it, the Prieſt, not having his hands at Liberty, made uſe of his mouth,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:65044:31"/> and blowed againſt the Fly, which not deſiſting hereupon, he made a ſign to the Deacon who preſented the Pax to the Biſhop, to drive it away. Then the Fly mounting up higher, and ſtopping a little, on a ſuddain fell down dead at the foot of the Chalice, as a puniſhment for the trouble ſhe had giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en them, during the Sacrifice. <hi>Caeſarius l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another like Puniſhment of another Fly.</head>
                  <p>ABout the year 1545. as one ſung the Conventual Maſs, in a Monaſtery of the <hi>Celeſtines,</hi> the Prieſt that celebrated, perceived at the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that a Fly was got into the Chalice, he endeavoured to catch it and to take it out, but all in vain; but ſeeing ſhe was diſturbed, of her own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord ſhe flew away. As the Prieſt after dinner was thanking God, that he had eſcaped this miſchance; the ſame Fly, came to ſettle upon the Arm of the V. F. Frier <hi>John Bardoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t,</hi> and tho' he ſhook his arm, yet ſhe continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed fixed. Then thinking of what had happened at Maſſe, he ſeized her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as yet wet with the Sacred Blood, after this he carried her into the Veſtry, where ſhe received the Penalty of her raſhneſs, according as it is commanded by the Canons. <hi>Gon. in hiſt. ejus l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 126.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Mule adores the Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>S. <hi>Anthony</hi> of <hi>Padua</hi> diſputing one day with one of the moſt obſtinate Hereticks, that denyed the truth of the H. Sacrament, the Saint drove him to ſuch a plunge, that he ſtood mute, yet ſo it was, that not being willing to confeſs that he was wholly convinced, he deſired that the Saint would prove this truth by ſome Miracle. S. <hi>Anthony</hi> accepted the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſaid he would work it upon his Mule. Upon this the Heretick kept her ſhut up three days without eating or drinking. The third day the Saint having ſaid Maſſe, took up the H. Hoſt with great reverence, and made them bring forth the hungry Mule; to which he ſpake in theſe termes. In the name of the Lord, whom I, tho' unworthy hold in my hands, I command thee without delay to come and do reverence to thy Creator, and confound the Malice of Hereticks, making every one under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Truth of this moſt high Sacrament, which we Prieſts handle at the Altar, and that all Creatures are ſubject to their Creator. Whilſt the Saint made this diſcourſe, the Heretick ſifted out Oats to his Mule to make him eat; but the Beaſt, having more underſtanding than his Maſter, without minding the Oats, kneeled and proſtrated it ſelf before the H. Sacrament, adoring and honouring it as its Creator and Lord. This Miracle comforted all the faithful, and enraged the Hereticks, except him who had diſputed with the Saint, who was converted to the Catholick Faith. <hi>Wadingus in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n. Minorum.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:65044:32"/>
                  <head>A Mule ſerves for an Occaſion to honour the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>IN the year 1453. on Thurſday the 6th of <hi>June,</hi> this following Miracle happen'd. A War being raiſed in <hi>Piedmont,</hi> between the Savoyards and the French, about certain Merchants Goods, that had been detained at <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>igtie;</hi> and the heat of the War increaſing, the Place was taken and left to pillage. A Souldier entred into the Church and carried away thence the Tabernacle of the H. Sacrament, where he had a conſecrated Hoſt; and having hid it in a Pack, marched towards <hi>Turin.</hi> When he arrived there at the Gate of <hi>Suſe,</hi> the Mule that carried the Goods and the Booty, fell down to the ground, neer the Church of S. <hi>Sylveſter.</hi> The Pack, where the Hoſts were, opened of it ſelf, and the Hoſt came forth, and flew up into the Air, accompanied with Splendors and caſting forth Rays like the Sun: This wonder having been ſeen by a venerable Perſon, called <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew Loconi,</hi> he went preſently to give notice of it to the Biſhop of <hi>Turin,</hi> who was at that time the Reverend <hi>Lewis Nomagnano,</hi> who came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without delay, with the Croſs and the Clergy. Being come to the place, he and all that were preſent kneeled down on the ground, and whilſt the Tabernacle lay on the Earth, the Hoſt alone remained hanging in the Air, brightly ſhining. Whereupon the Biſhop made them bring the Chalice, and ſtanding with it devoutly under the Sacred Hoſt, it came down into it; which he carried with great Reſpect and Solemnity to the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral Church; where there was ſet up for it a rich and artificial Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, which continued till the building of a new <hi>Dome,</hi> for to perpetuate the memory of the Fact. There was alſo built a Chappel of the H. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the foreſaid Church of S. <hi>Sylveſter,</hi> where this Miracle is to be ſeen painted, and he erected a devout Fraternity alſo of the H. Sacrament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nic. de Laghi tract.</hi> 1. <hi>diſt.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 93.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Mule by Dying acknowledges the Verity of the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>A Little Town in <hi>Spain</hi> called <hi>Aroca,</hi> containing about a thouſand Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, being beſieged by an infinite number of Saracens, the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants reſolved to defend themſelves, but ſo as they would firſt receive the Communion and hear Maſſe. The affair was preſſing, and therefore they committed the buſineſs of communicating to ſix of the chief of them. The Prieſt put on his H. Veſtments to celebrate, and conſecrated the Hoſts; but a little before the Communion, news came that an Aſſault was made by the Enemies; which obliged theſe Communicants to run armed to the Walk, and God accepting the will for the deed, did ſo favour theſe devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of his, that they defeated the Enemies, ſome being ſlain, and the reſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:65044:32"/> put to flight. After which, theſe ſix returned to the Church, with the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to receive the Communion. But the Corporal (or Cloath) being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded, the ſix Hoſts were found all bloody and ſticking to the Linnen, ſo that they could not ſeparate them. Moreover the Enemies, to revenge their diſgrace, returning in greater numbers, gave a ſecond Aſſault. The adviſe given was, that the Prieſt ſhould alſo go to the Fight, bearing the H. Corporal and theſe ſix bloody Hoſtes, as well thereby to encourage the Citizens, as for to terrify the Enemies; and it ſucceeded ſo well, that God gave the victory to the Chriſtians. After this, they deliberated, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſhould carry this parcel of H. Reliques, ſo as to be ſafely kept and honoured. The Lot being thrice caſt, it fell upon the Town of <hi>Aroca.</hi> A Mule having been taken among the Spoiles of the Enemy, they ſet the H. Hoſts upon her back, letting her go whither ſhe would, the Clergy and People following her with lighted Torches. In the way they offered to her Straw, Hay, and Graſs, all which ſhe refuſed, thô ſhe was very hungry, as not having eaten a long while, and went on ſtraight to the Town of <hi>Aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca.</hi> Coming into a Church nigh the Hoſpital, ſhe fell on her knees on the ground, and being disburdned of this pretious load, ſhe dyed; it being undecent, that ſhe which had ſerved in ſo worthy an Employment, for the Glory of God, ſhould ſerve any Man after that. There was another wonder in this matter, <hi>viz.</hi> That after three hundred years, this moſt H. parcel of Reliques, continues in the ſame beauty, and lively colour, as if the thing had but newly happened; and all the People of the neighbouring Provinces come to behold it, as a very great Wonder. <hi>Illercas in Hiſt. Pontifical. Grenade. Corbin. Mirac.</hi> 90.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="O" type="part">
               <head>O.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Oiſeau.</hi> A Bird.</note>A Bird brings S. <hi>Boniface</hi> and the Company with him, their Dinner, after he had celebrated Maſs.</head>
                  <p>S. <hi>Boniface</hi> the Apoſtle of <hi>Germany,</hi> being one Night detained in the Fields, was conſtrained to lodge in a Tent, which he cauſed to be carried with him for ſuch occaſions. He paſſed the night in Prayer, and as he prayed, a coeleſtial Light ſurrounded him on all ſides, and in this Light S. <hi>Michael</hi> appeared, encouraging the Servant of God to labour greatly for the Salvation and Converſion of Soules. In the morning giving over his praying, he would celebrate the Maſſe, to honour the memory of this Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angel; the Sacrifice being ended, he commanded to make ready a Dinner in the ſame place. And when his Steward told him that he had nothing to ſet on the Table: How! reply'd the great Apoſtle, he that fed his People 40 years in the Wilderneſs, has he nothing wherewith to feed his poor Servant, and his Attendants? then he again commanded them to ſpread the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:65044:33"/> Table: and having ſaid this, behold he ſaw a great Bird deſcend from Heaven, and fly towards him, holding in her beake a Fiſh, ſufficient to feed, that day, all the company. When the Fiſh was ready dreſſed, it was ſet on the Table, and after all had liberally ſatisfyed nature, at the concluſion of the day, the H. Apoſtle commanded to gather up the remains, and to caſt them into the River, that ſo the Fiſhes that live in the water might partake of that which came out of the water. <hi>In vita S. Bonifacii.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A fine Bird came to cheer a Monk with her melodious Singing, after he had received the Communion, as if ſhe invited him to Heaven.</head>
                  <p>A Monk of the <hi>Carthuſian Order,</hi> drawing towards Death, after he had received the Communion; a Bird decked with fine feathers, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered at his Window into the Chamber, where in preſence of all the Friers, that aſſiſted the dying man, ſhe fell a ſinging ſo melodiouſly, that it ſeemed to them all that they were ſolaced with the joys of Paradiſe: Some that were there indeavoured to make her void the Chamber, but in vain; for ſhe would neither fly out nor ceaſe ſinging, till the Servant of God had yielded his Soul, which when it went out of his Body, the Bird quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Chamber, for to accompany it and conduct it to Heaven. <hi>Pet. Sutor. in Chron. Cartuſ. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 33.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ours.</hi> A Bear.</note>A Bear ſerves for a ſubject to honour the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>A Perſon named <hi>Staniſlas,</hi> an Inhabitant of the Town of <hi>Fuchol</hi> in <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> uſed to go a Hunting with a long Harquebuſs. Being entred the Foreſt, he ſaw a Beaſt called <hi>Gallus Auritus,</hi> which leaping from one bough to another, led the man on to a certain place full of tufts of wild Trees, where there was no Pathway. Mean while he was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed with a ſhowre of Rain, which to avoyd, he reſted himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Tree, where he fell aſleep. Whilſt he ſlept, he heard a Voice that ſaid to him, Make a Vow to the H. Body of Jeſus Chriſt, who is honour'd at <hi>Poſnanie,</hi> and thou ſhalt be ſaved to day from ſudden Death. His wearineſs keeping him aſleep, he heard the ſame Voice again; upon which awaking, he recommended himſelf to God, and made a Vow to go to the H. Sacrament at <hi>Poſnanie,</hi> yet apprehending no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. But purſuing his way, he met a great and very furious Bear, againſt which he diſcharged his Harquebuſs, and layd the Bear on the ground: whil'ſt he was bending the Cock to diſcharge a ſecond ſhot, it through negligence ſlipt and went off, and the Bullet carried away
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:65044:33"/> the little finger of his right hand, and ſtruck off his hat, which it tore alſo in peices. Hereupon finding himſelf delivered from two dangers the ſame day, by vertue of his Vow, without further delay he began his Journey to accompliſh it, and arrived at <hi>Poſnanie</hi> on Saturday in the Octave of the Feaſt of All Saints, in the year 1530. <hi>Treterus apud Bzovium ad ann.</hi> 1399. <hi>Pag.</hi> 206. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="P" type="part">
               <head>P.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Paſſereau.</hi> A Sparrow.</note>Sparrows by their Obedience and their Death, teſtify their regard to the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>JOhn Herolt,</hi> a <hi>Dominican,</hi> reports that Sparrows having uſed to build their Neſts in a Church dedicated to S. <hi>Vincent</hi> the Martyr, not onely defiled it with their dung and ordure, but alſo diſturbed the divine Office. It being a very hard thing to drive them away, the Biſhop of the place brought an Excommunication againſt them, threatning death to them, if they returned thither any more. After the Sentence was paſſed, all theſe Sparrows quitted this Church: it was alſo obſerved, that if any brought one of theſe Birds into the Church, it immediately dyed. <hi>Serm.</hi> 79. <hi>de tempore.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Partridges chaſtiſe the Hunter, who had taken them, for having been defective in attending Maſſe, and flew away, tho they were put into the Pot.</head>
                  <p>IN the Dioceſs of <hi>Caſal</hi> in <hi>Piedmont,</hi> a Hunter minding more to take his Pleaſure in that Sport, than to hear Maſſe on the Martyr S. <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi>'s Day, took indeed ſome Partridges; but as they were put into the Pot to boyl them, they came out and flew away alive: leaving the Hunter in the dark, and deprived of the Contentment of filling his Belly, with the loſs alſo of the Merit he might have gained, by being preſent at the H. Sacrifice of the Maſſe. <hi>Bollandus in actis SS. Januarii ad</hi> 2 <hi>diem.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">Poiſſons. <hi>Fiſhes.</hi>
                     </note>Fiſhes honour the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>THe Curate of <hi>Alboraya</hi> in the Kingdome of <hi>Valentia</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> carrying the H. Sacrament to a ſick Perſon of <hi>Almacora,</hi> which is a dependant joyned to that Curacy; as he paſſed over a Brook, ſuch a Torrent of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters came down upon him, that to ſave himſelf he let fall the Cuſtode (or Box) in which were two Hoſts. Returning to <hi>Alboraya,</hi> he told the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:65044:34"/> of what had happened to him. In the morning early, one ran with all ſpeed to the place, where this misfortune happened, but he found only the Cuſtode without the Hoſts. Certain Fiſhermen paſſing along the Sea ſide, whether to gather Wood, or to catch Fiſh, told him they had ſeen two great Fiſhes, each of them carrying an Hoſte in its mouth. The Curate being advertiſed of it, returned to the Sea ſide, habited in his Surplice and Stole, with the Chalice in his hand. Upon the ſight of this wonder, he proſtrated himſelf before the Fiſhes, which rendred themſelves to him with the Hoſts, which he received and layd them in the Chalice, with great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence. In memory of which, the Chalice is to be ſeen at <hi>Alboraya,</hi> and the Cuſtode at <hi>Almacora.</hi> And to prevent ſuch inconveniences, in the year 1352, this Town before joyned, was ſeparated from the principal Pariſh, after many debates and conteſts between theſe two places. This whole Hiſtory is painted at the great Altar of <hi>Almacora,</hi> erected under the Title of the moſt Holy Sacrament. <hi>James Bleda, in his Book of the Fraternity of the H Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament erected at the Minerva in Rome. Mirac.</hi> 18. <hi>pag.</hi> 89.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another reſpect, rendred by a Fiſh to the H. Hoſt.</head>
                  <p>WHilſt the Hereſy of the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> infected all the Province of <hi>Narbonna</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> an Heretick perſwaded a certain Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that if he would thrive in his Calling, he ſhould go to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and from thence bring away the Hoſt, and make a Fiſh eat it, which he did. Twenty years after, when this Hereſy was extinct, this Fiſherman ſeeing that the Feaſt of our Lords Body was celebrated with ſo much ſolemnity, he repented of the Sin he had committed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed it to his Curate, who told him that this was a reſerved caſe, and that he ought to acquaint the Biſhop with it. The Fiſherman, in great wrath ſaid, If I muſt do this, I ſwear by God, I will never go to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion more. Hereupon the Curate for to pacify him, ſaid, that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf would go find out the Biſhop, and get leave of him that he might abſolve him. Eaſter Day came, and the Fiſherman had a deſire to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with his Neighbours, which yet he did not, following the advice of his Prieſt. Mean while the Fiſherman bewailing his diſgrace, went ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfully towards the River where he had committed this Sacriledge: as he looked this way and that way, behold he ſpied on the other ſide of the River a Fiſh, holding in his mouth an Hoſt, which came towards him, but not daring to touch it, he went to give notice of it to the Prieſt: and both comming to that ſame place, the Fiſh appeared no more. Hereat conceiving great diſpleaſure, a little after, the Fiſh appeared again a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove water, with the Hoſt in her mouth as before, and being come up to them, the Prieſt with all reſpect took up the Fiſh with the Hoſt.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:65044:34"/> He kept a moiety of it for the Pariſh, and ſent the other part to the Cathedral Church. <hi>Id. Bleda</hi> 1. <hi>Mirac.</hi> 104. <hi>p.</hi> 191. <hi>Lanuza in ſuis Sermonibus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Whale, a Fiſh of the greater kind, lent his Back to ſay Maſſe upon, on Eaſter-Day.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rius</hi> reports that S. <hi>Malo</hi> being upon the Sea on a Eaſter Day, prayed the good God, to afford him the means to celebrate the Maſſe, and to thoſe that accompanied him to hear it. When he had thus prayed, one perceived a little Iſland, which appeared in the midſt of the Sea: they went down upon it, to the number of a Hundred and eighty Perſons; they ſet up an Altar, on which S. <hi>Malo</hi> ſaid Maſſe, and gave the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion to a great number. After which retiring to their Ship, they perceived that this Iſland, or rather the Fiſh ſunk to the bottom, having lent his Back, as God would have it, to ſatisfie the Saints deſire.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Surius in Vita S. Maclonii.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">Pourceau. <hi>Swine.</hi>
                     </note>Swine adore the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>A Certain Woman not being able to believe that God was in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, was tempted by the Devil, to take ſome proof from thence to ſatisfie her fanſie, and althô her Confeſſor, and alſo <hi>Albert</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Peruſia</hi> had exhorted her to yield to the publick belief, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by ſo many knowing and vertuous Perſons, without deſiring to be inſtructed and confirmed herein by a Miracle, notwithſtanding after all, ſhe was led away by her fancy to make the Trial. She went therefore one day to the Communion, and having taken the Hoſt out of her mouth, ſhe went and threw it into the Hogs-trough, which upon the Noiſe ſhe made ran greedily to their trough: but being alltogether, inſtead of opening their mouth to ſwallow the Hoſt, they kneeled down to adore it. The unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Woman ſtopt not here; but put the Hoſt upon the Spit to roaſt it at the fire. As ſhe turned the Spit, ſhe ſaw drops of Blood that diſtilled from the Hoſt: notwithſtanding ſhe continued ſtubbornly in her falſe Opinion, and being afraid to be apprehended and put to death, if what ſhe had done ſhould be diſcovered; ſhe digged a hole in the ground and there buried the Hoſt, that it might be ſpoken of no more. But ſhe perceiving that the Blood bubled out of the Earth, and ran in abundance like a Spring, the hardneſs of her heart was ſoftned: ſo that her underſtanding being inlightned in this Truth, and repenting of her unbelief, ſhe went to find out the foreſaid Biſhop of <hi>Perouſe,</hi> who having
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:65044:35"/> heard her confeſſion, impoſed a Penance on her to perform, during her whole life. <hi>Henr. Inſtit. p.</hi> 1. <hi>Serm.</hi> 9. <hi>Biga ſalutis in feſto Corp. Chriſti Prompt. Diſcip. Exem.</hi> 33. <hi>l. E.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="R" type="part">
               <head>R.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Renard.</hi> A Fox.</note>A Fox quits the Hen he had carried away, by vertue of the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>S. <hi>Gregory</hi> the Pope tells us, that S. <hi>Boniface,</hi> whilſt he was a young Child, ſtanding at the Dore of his Lodging; he perceived a Fox running away with a Hen in his mouth. Immediately away he went to the Church, and placing himſelf before the H. Sacrament, he made this Prayer to it. Lord I beſeech thee be pleaſed to preſerve the Pullen which my Mother feeds in her back-yard, for the ſuſtenance of her little Family. Having done this, he returned to his Lodging, where this Fox appeared again with the Hen in his mouth, and laying down the Hen, fell down dead at the feet of this Child. <hi>S. Gregor. Dialog. l.</hi> 1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Roſſignol.</hi> A Nightingale.</note>A Nightingale advertiſes a Devout Frier to prepare for his Voyage to Heaven, for his having a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Inclination to attend Maſſes.</head>
                  <p>THe Bl. <hi>John de Rieti,</hi> a moſt excellent <hi>Auguſtinian Frier,</hi> had a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular devotion to attend on as many Maſſes as he could poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly, for the reverence he bore to the H. Sacrament of the Altar and confidence he had in it. See now the recompence which our Lord made him; a few days before his laſt Sickneſs, a Nightingale came every day to ſing her warbling Notes under his Window. Being asked, what was the meaning of this, he anſwer'd, that this was the Spouſe that invited him to the Banquet of the Lamb. Alſo, a few days after, attending at Maſſe, he ſaw an extraordinary Light, which continued all the time of the Sacrifice, which he took for a Star that was to conduct him to Heaven. At length, he fell ſick, and having been armed by receiving the Sacraments, and having repeated thoſe words of the Apoſtle, <hi>I deſire to be diſſolved and to be with Chriſt,</hi> he left the Earth that he might partake of the Banquet, of the Lamb, to which he was invited.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Simplician de S. Martin, in the Hiſtory of famous Men of the Order of the Hermits of S. Auguſtine.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="S" type="part">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:65044:35"/>
               <head>S.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Scorpion taken and ſwallowed down at Maſſe, hurts not the Prieſt at all that did it.</head>
                  <p>THe Bl. <hi>Francis de Fabriano,</hi> a <hi>Franciſcan</hi> Frier, celebrating Maſſe one day, as he was come to the Communion, and took off the Cover of the Chalice, he perceived there a little Scorpion: he might have kept himſelf from all danger, obſerving the Rules preſcribed in ſuch caſes, but calling to mind the Saying of Jeſus Chriſt to his Diſciples, <hi>if they drink any deadly thing it ſhall not hurt them;</hi> baniſhing all fear, and overcoming all horror, he courage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſwallowed the conſecrated Wine with this little Animal in it. When he was gone back from the Altar and had offered his thankſgivings, he made them call a Chirurgeon. When he came into the Convent, Bl. <hi>Francis</hi> was praying in that Church and repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe words, <hi>My help is of the Lord, who made Heaven and Earth.</hi> When notice was given him that the Surgeon was come, he went into his Cell, and there preſented to him his right Arm to let him Blood; and out of it, by a ſtrange wonder, the Scorpion came out alive with the Blood, without doing the H. man any harm, or put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him to peine. <hi>Waddingus tom.</hi> 3. <hi>ad ann.</hi> 1312. <hi>n.</hi> 7. <hi>Nic. de Lag tr.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sanglier.</hi> A wild Boar.</note>A Wild Boar ſhows what reſpect is due to Altars, the Sacred Manſions of the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>IN the year 1032. <hi>Sanchy</hi> the Aged, King of <hi>Navarr</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtille,</hi> going a hunting, at the place where ſometime ſtood the Town of <hi>Palence,</hi> he there purſued a wild Boar, which tiring after a long chaſe, caſt it ſelf into Sanctuary among the Ruines of the Church of S. <hi>Antony</hi> the Martyr, and there ſtood unmoved againſt the Altar, as in a place of ſafety, and having ordinarily the guard of Angels; the King entring on a ſudden, lifted up his Sword to wound it, but when he thought to diſcharge his blow at it, his Arm became ſtiff, ſo that he could not uſe it. Whereupon he acknowledged his fault, ſince Churches where God uſes to dwell in the H. Euchariſt, ought to ſerve for an Aſylum and a refuge to Men and Beaſts, according to the Divine Oracle, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35. <hi>Thou Lord ſhalt ſave both men and beaſts.</hi> Immediately he asked Pardon of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:65044:36"/> God and the H. Martyr; and immediately by a Miracle he recovered the uſe of his Arm; teaching all, what reſpect is due to holy Places, altho ruined, ſince Beaſts may there find their ſafety. This Prodigy gave an occaſion to King <hi>Sanchy,</hi> not onely to repair the Church of S. <hi>Antonin,</hi> but alſo to cauſe the Town of <hi>Palence</hi> to be rebuilded.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Roder. Tolet. l.</hi> 6. <hi>Regum Hiſpan. c.</hi> 6. <hi>Rod. Sancius, c.</hi> 25.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sauterelles.</hi> Locuſts or Graſhoppers.</note>Locuſts or Graſhoppers acknowledge the vertue of the Euchariſt, and of the H. Sacrifice, by their Death.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rius</hi> reports in the Life of S. <hi>Theodore,</hi> 22d of April, that the H. Abbot was preſſed by the Inhabitants of <hi>Neran,</hi> that he would help them againſt the Armies of Locuſts, that had inveſted like a thick miſt, all the Fields of that Territory, and went on brouzing and conſuming all the Herbs and Fruits of the ground. The H. Abbot was perſwaded by their inſtant intreaties, and comming upon the place, he ſaid Maſſe. The day following, he ſent again the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple into the Fields, commanding them to ſtop at a certain place, for to implore the divine aid; mean while he took up in his hands ſome of theſe Locuſts, and found them dead. Hereupon he gave God thanks, and ſaid to the People, My Children return to the Churches, and you ſhall ſee the Miracles of the divine Goodneſs. All the People being come thither, S. <hi>Theodore</hi> celebrated the H. Sacrifice of the Maſſe, and the day following, they found in the Field an innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable company of Locuſts, all lying dead; which inſtead of depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating the Fields, ſerved to manure and enrich them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Souris.</hi> A Mouſe.</note>Mice, by a certain cogniſance, yield reſpect to the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CEſarius</hi> tells us, that the Sacriſt of the Abbey of <hi>Eberbac,</hi> having found certain Hoſts marred and crack'd mixed among others, he caſt them under a Window neer to the Altar; and ſome days after, he obſerved, that the Mice had nibled and eaten all that which was round the Hoſt <hi>(not what was Printed with Letters)</hi> and it was held for a great Wonder, that theſe little Animals, ſo greedy of ſuch ſtuff, had ſpared them, in teſtimony of certain reſpect, and onely becauſe they had been appointed for the uſe of the Sacrifice of the Maſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>about the year</hi> 1222.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="T" type="part">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:65044:36"/>
               <head>T.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Taureau.</hi> A Bull.</note>A Bull acknowledges our Lord, under the Species of the Sacrament, depoſing its fierceneſs, to be preſent at the Maſſe.</head>
                  <p>IN the Town of <hi>Broſa</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> may be ſeen an admirable Prodigy, which has been ſeen many years ago, and may ſtill be ſeen every year, on the Veſpers and day of S. <hi>Mark</hi> the <hi>Evangeliſt.</hi> In this place is a Fraternity under the Title of S. <hi>Mark,</hi> to which Heaven has given this Priviledge following. <hi>viz.</hi> That at the Feaſt of this H. Evangeliſt, this Congregation makes choice of one of their Company, whom they ſend into the Fields, where he demands of the Neat-heard that looks to the Cattle, which of his Bulls is the moſt fierce and furious. When he has learnt this, he commands this Bull, in the name of S. <hi>Mark,</hi> to follow him, which like a tame Lamb follows him to the Village, and is preſent at Veſpers on the Eve of this Feaſt; after which, he returns to the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and the next day he preſents himſelf on the ſame manner at Maſſe, where the true Lamb of God is ſacrificed; after this he marches in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion in the ſame Poſture, and ſuffers the Boys and Girles to touch him, and put Wreaths of Flowers about his Neck. This Feaſt and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony being over, he is ſent back to the Herd, and reſumes immediately his wonted and natural fierceneſs, and from that time People muſt have a care of him. <hi>P. Bibero in append. Solemnis ſapientiae convivii.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="U" type="part">
               <head>U.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vache.</hi> A Cow.</note>A Cow revenges an Injury done to the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>IN the year 1650. in a Town of the Province of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> called in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguarinum;</hi> on an Eaſter Eve when they were buſy in a Proceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, according to the Cuſtome of the Country, carrying the H. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in great Pomp, amidſt Acclamations, many Vollies of Guns ſhot off, and the noyſe of Kettle-drums, Trumpets and Tabours, an old Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter's Wife, fell into a rage, through deſpite to ſee the honour they gave to God in the H. Euchariſt, and cryed out furiouſly with full mouth; Behold, ſays ſhe, the Papiſts have again raiſed their Chriſt, whom they put to death three days agoe. This Blaſphemy was immediately pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh'd; for a Cow, that came no body knew from whence, and followed this Fury, on a ſuddain being as it were pricked forward by an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:65044:37"/> indignation, ran furiouſly againſt this Heretick; and having puſhed and gored her back with her horns, ruſh'd her down ſo wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that ſhe expired a few hours after, to be preſented before him whom ſhe had blaſphemed, who is the Judge of Quick and Dead. <hi>P. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſi in literis annuis ad an. Cit. prov. Auſtriae par.</hi> 3.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">Vers. <hi>Wormes.</hi>
                     </note>Wormes are found dead, for having eaten up the Flowers deſigned for the honour of the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>IN the Convent of S. <hi>Catherine</hi> in the Province of <hi>Valentia,</hi> a Lay-Brother called <hi>Aſſenſius,</hi> one of great Faith and Devotion towards the H. Sacrament of the Altar, lookt to a little Garden of Flowers he had, which he made uſe of to ſpread before the H. Euchariſt. On the Eve of <hi>Corpus Chriſti</hi> day, he went into his Garden to look on his Flowers, which he ſaw there growing very freſh and in great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, of which he was extreamly glad: but in the Morning going in to gather them, he perceived a number of Wormes all round about which had eaten them up and conſumed them. In this ſtreight, he ran haſtily to the H. Sacrament, and after he had adored it, he ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly beſeeched it to deliver him from his Sorrows, by reſtoring the Flowers he had reſerved, for the honour of his moſt H. Body. In confidence that our Lord had heard his Prayer, he returned to his Garden, and found it all ſmiling with freſh and fair Flowers, and thoſe little Vermin lying dead, to enrich the Ground. This great Devotion which he had teſtified all his life time towards the H. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, obtained for him the happineſs to expire and render his Soul to his Creator, in the preſence of the moſt Glorious Virgin Mother, of her dear Son our Lord, and of his ſeraphick Father S. <hi>Francis,</hi> on the H. Night of Chriſtmaſs. <hi>Franc. Gouraga de brig. &amp; rog. Seraph. Rel. S. Franc.</hi> 3. <hi>p. in prov. Valent. con.</hi> 12.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Wormes revenge the Injury done to the H. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>A Thunderbolt having by God's Providence, fallen upon <hi>Apollo</hi>'s Temple in <hi>Daphne,</hi> the building was beat down and lay in Aſhes. <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate attributing this burning to the Zeal of the Chriſtians, commanded that all the H. Veſſels of Gold and Silver of great Value, in the great Church built by <hi>Conſtantin,</hi> ſhould be brought into the Emperour's Exchequer as forfeited. Among thoſe Perſons that were moſt ready to execute this Order, was <hi>Julian,</hi> this Emperour's Uncle, who governed the Empire of the Eaſt; who
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:65044:37"/> was ſuddenly ſtruck with a Malady, that held him for forty days ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing along on the ground, without Speech or Senſe. The cauſe of this ſudden Malady was attributed to what he had done in ſeizing upon the H. Veſſels, as Pixes, Chalices and ſuch others, which he had bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in pieces, and had made them up for a Seat to ſit on. He recovered indeed his Senſes, but it was to feel extraordinary Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in his Bowels, where ſtrange Ulcers bred with ſo much cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, that all the Fleſh ran into Wormes, which tho' they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd by applications to allure as it were and draw them forth, yet inſtead of that, they went further inward, and faſtened themſelves to the live Fleſh, and never ceaſed to torment him, till he had vomited out his Soul, at his infamous and noyſome mouth. <hi>Niceph. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt. in hiſt. Eccleſ. l.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 29.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Vipers honour the H. Sacrament, by quitting thoſe whom they had afflicted.</head>
                  <p>IN the year 1651. at <hi>Breſte,</hi> a Town in <hi>Poland,</hi> a great Lady was moleſted for ſome while with ſo ſtrange a Witchery, that ſhe vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited live Vipers and Froggs, which cauſed horrour to all thoſe that heard her ſpeak of it, and to her ſelf who was afflicted thereby with very great torment. She adviſed with our Fathers about it, and from them ſhe learnt, that there was not a more ſoveraign and effectual Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy againſt ſuch Witcheries, than to approach the H. Euchariſt with a great Faith and Confidence. She made uſe of this advice with ſuch ſucceſs, that at length ſhe found her ſelf releaſed and quit of this Witchcraft, and reſtored to that health and quiet, which ſhe enjoyed before this Misfortune. <hi>Ex Literis annuis Poloniae,</hi> 1651. 5. <hi>Nadaſi.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:65044:38"/>
            <head>The LICENSE,</head>
            <p>THeſe Hiſtories taken out of Catholick Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, and containing nothing contrary to Faith or good Manners, may be made publick,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at <hi>Lille.</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>June</hi> 20. 1672.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>R. Du Laury,</hi> Provoſt of S. <hi>Peters.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:65044:38"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
